<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Derek Willis</title>
<link>https://www.thescoop.org/blog.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://www.thescoop.org/blog.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Academic and journalist</description>
<generator>quarto-1.2.269</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2022 05:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Welcome Back</title>
  <dc:creator>Derek Willis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2022/12/31/welcome-back/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>It feels like a good time to start writing again, but this isn’t a totally fresh start. As I’ve tried to de-emphasize the time and attention that I’ve given to Twitter over the past few years, I realized that I still have things that I want to talk about. I don’t have a newsletter, or a podcast. But since 1998 or so, I have had a blog, and that’s what I’m coming back to.</p>
<p>I’ve rebuilt this site to combine what used to be “here” on thescoop.org and some of what had been sitting around in other places. There are and will be more personal posts here, but the focus will be on what I like to write about: the combination of data, journalism and learning. Since joining the faculty at <a href="https://merrill.umd.edu/">Merrill College</a>, I’ve had so many questions and discussions with my colleagues near and far about teaching: what works and doesn’t, and what we could try. So there will be a fair bit of that here.</p>
<p>The move to academia also has given me a bit more freedom in terms of what I can say about this profession and how it is changing. I’ve spent the past year learning R and with this rebuild I’m able to share code in a way that hopefully is more useful, too.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2022/12/31/welcome-back/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2022 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The More Important Problem</title>
  <dc:creator>Derek Willis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2019/03/09/the-more-important-problem/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The first indication that I did not approach this <a href="http://thescoop.org/archives/2019/02/24/making-the-best-nicar-listserv/">NICAR-L improvement project</a> in the right way should have been when I posted on GitHub a CSV file with metadata from 16 years’ of posts to the listserv. Not long after, I got a message saying that maybe I should take it down because it disclosed individuals’ email addresses.</p>
<p>“Huh,” I thought. “Why would it be a problem for journalists’ emails to be public?” I asked myself, a guy who has been on the listserv for more than 20 years whose worst experience on it consists of people I respect dunking on me in a way that I wouldn’t object to. The social and professional risk of posting on the listserv is low for me, but not for everyone. The Internet, by and large, has been a pretty safe place for me, but not for everyone.</p>
<p>If I needed any reinforcement of that initial indication, it came when I looked at the small group of people who showed up at <a href="https://www.ire.org/events-and-training/event/3433/4362/">the conference session</a> to talk about ways to improve the listserv experience. The folks who came – all good, smart people – had this much in common: they were, like me, white guys. I had billed the session as an attempt to explore technical solutions that would make the listserv more useful for its expanding community of users. Maybe even a chance to restore the listserv’s culture to what it had been in the days when the community numbered in the hundreds, not the thousands. You know, when it was mostly guys like me who shared a lot of the same experiences.</p>
<p>That I had not really thought much about how different people experience the listserv differently says a lot about the actual challenge we face in trying to make NICAR-L more useful for everyone (and something about me, too). The easier lesson is that technical solutions may be necessary to achieve the goal of a better listserv, but they are not sufficient. The harder - and more important - lesson is that if we want things to improve, we’ll need to think hard about what factors into individual decisions to post and not post, and what kind of community we want. Otherwise the technical work won’t be addressing the more important problem.</p>
<p>There’s a <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/13QdI3J8GQm-ECFsQx6Bllwrz2epZ6BXdtV2bsRAQxeI/edit?usp=sharing">Google doc</a> from our initial discussion that includes some potential goals and ideas we talked about. All of them are possible and many of them could make a real difference, even if only in a small way. I don’t think any of them are outlandish or techno-utopianism run amok. (You can, if you like, comment on them.)</p>
<p>But the idea that we could make fundamental improvements in the listserv experience without addressing the culture that surrounds it is folly. We can’t recommend NICAR-L to students and newcomers and then expect them to magically know how to adjust to whatever tone and culture they find if we don’t define the culture we want and build the processes that encourage it. We also can’t consider the listserv in isolation. The NICAR crowd has other options for sharing knowledge and building community, from Slack to affinity groups, and those are unlikely to disappear. Those competitors might help inform how we consider the listserv, too.</p>
<p>So what’s the current culture of NICAR-L? I’m not sure I have a good answer, because my own perception is influenced by how I experienced it 15-20 years ago. One of the participants at the conference session said he doesn’t post because he’s not sure who is on the listserv. When I was an active participant that wasn’t a concern for me. Now, I get the sense that NICAR-L is not as homogenous as it was (which is a good thing for many reasons) and that there’s also greater uncertainty about what the listserv is for and what people should expect from it. That’s a shame, because I really believe that there is a lot of value not just in the archives but in the current membership. But in my excitement about the possibilities, I looked right past the idea that human problems often require human intervention.</p>
<p>Here’s what I’m going to do: I’d still like to explore some of the ideas that were raised at the conference session, with the goal of trying to understand the culture of the listserv and how we all react to it. And I’d like to do what I can to encourage all of us to talk about what we want from the listserv and what we need to get there. For me, one step is to re-engage more on the listserv. Ultimately, technology will only make a difference if we have clear understanding of the problems we’re trying to solve and if we’re willing to have an open conversation about the kind of culture we want to have.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2019/03/09/the-more-important-problem/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2019 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The NICAR-L Improvement Project</title>
  <dc:creator>Derek Willis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2019/02/24/making-the-best-nicar-listserv/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>If you’re coming to the <a href="https://www.ire.org/events-and-training/conferences/nicar-2019">2019 CAR Conference</a> in March, chances are you’re a member of the <a href="https://www.ire.org/resource-center/listservs/subscribe-to-nicar-l">NICAR-L listserv</a>. The only session idea I pitched this year was on <a href="https://www.ire.org/events-and-training/event/3433/4362/">how to make the listserv better</a>, and I’d love your help.</p>
<p>Listservs are fascinating social experiments. People join, ask questions of strangers and then hopefully through discussion become fuller members of a community. When it works, it’s one of the best things about the Internet. When it doesn’t, the whole point of a listserv - the sharing of knowledge - falls apart. NICAR-L is no different from any other listserv, but because IRE is a member-driven organization, we’ve got a chance to make real improvements using the skills we have.</p>
<p>If you’ve been a member of NICAR-L as long as I have – since at least 1997, as near as I can figure – then you know how much it has changed. There are many more people on it now, which is really great. Interest in our little corner of the journalism world has grown and people want to figure out how we do what we do. That growth naturally brings some challenges with it.</p>
<p>Here’s one example: about six years ago I made a new Gmail label: “Best of NICAR”. That was my way of dealing with a listserv that, in my view, suffered from a lot of repeat questions and the loss of shared understanding that can happen when a community experiences rapid growth. I know that I interact less on the listserv, and I’m pretty sure I’m not alone in that.</p>
<p>To be very clear: NICAR-L’s growth is itself a very good thing, particularly in that it has brought different voices into our community with different ideas and problems. When I joined IRE, the CAR conference was attended by 300-400 people, mostly white men with very similar interests and backgrounds. Many of the questions on the listserv were ones that a lot of us had in our minds, which made the conversation “easier” if not better.</p>
<p>We cannot and should not attempt to return to the time when most CAR conference attendees knew of each other (or actually knew each other). We should try to have a listserv that provides the kind of guidance and community that I was fortunate to have as a younger journalist.</p>
<p>The CAR conference session this year is pretty vaguely defined, and there’s a limit to what we can accomplish in an hour. That’s why I’m writing this, to put forth my hopes and (this being the CAR conference) some data we can use. This isn’t a fixed road map, just a starting point.</p>
<p>Some possible goals:</p>
<ul>
<li>Making the most useful posts and threads easier to find.</li>
<li>Creating a categorization scheme of some kind, or adapting an existing one.</li>
<li>Making it possible for users to provide feedback on the usefulness of posts.</li>
<li>A better UI for the listserv archive.</li>
<li>Making it easier to find answers to common questions.</li>
</ul>
<p>Many of these would require a separate web app, and while IRE has been extremely encouraging of this effort, I think it’s difficult to expect the organization to, say, redirect money dedicated to newsroom trainings towards listserv improvement. What might make such improvements more likely is the active involvement of IRE members. That’s where you come in.</p>
<p>IRE has very helpfully provided listserv archives from 2002 to the end of 2018. We’ll make those available to session attendees, although I’m not posting them on the Internet. As a starter, however, I’ve <a href="https://github.com/dwillis/nicarl-archives">posted on GitHub</a> a basic Python parser and metadata from each of the postings.</p>
<p>Some possible questions to explore:</p>
<ul>
<li>Can we identify valuable or interesting threads?</li>
<li>Can we identify common questions repeated often?</li>
<li>Are there categorization schemes we can apply to posts or even post metadata?</li>
</ul>
<p>What else can we do to make NICAR-L better? Feel free to add an issue on the GitHub repository or even post a thread on the listserv!</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2019/02/24/making-the-best-nicar-listserv/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 24 Feb 2019 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Best Training</title>
  <dc:creator>Derek Willis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2018/04/05/the-best-training/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I’ve been asked by students what the best training is to be a journalist. My position on this is very clear: waiting tables at a honeymoon resort is the best training.</p>
<p>No, really, that’s it. After you’ve delivered breakfast in bed to people who arrived late the night before, probably hammered, and now in the early morning can’t find the door, much less their pants, you can pretty much deal with any sort of situation that requires human interaction.</p>
<p>Interviewing strangers can be hard. But most of them are at least wearing some clothes, which reduces the awkwardness, you know?</p>
<p>I spent four summers and various holidays at a honeymoon resort in the Pocono Mountains of Pennsylvania, one of the places with those giant fiberglass jacuzzis shaped like champagne glasses. Should you go, please listen carefully: the instructions say you put a CAP-ful of bubble bath into the jacuzzi. Because it’s a jacuzzi, not a bath for an infant. If you pour the whole bottle in, you get that TV commercial where the bubbles grow eyes and fan out across the floor like an invading army. Housekeeping will hate you even more, and that’s an achievement for people who are cleaning up after you and your beloved have tried out the place, if you know what I mean. One cap-ful. I can’t set the breakfast tray down if the table is covered by 3 feet of bubbles.</p>
<p>Here’s how it works: I’d drive a golf cart equipped with a tray-carrying back up to your door, grab the trays and start knocking. You could always tell if a couple was new because you’d hear them crashing into unfamiliarly-placed furniture on their way downstairs. There are windows in some of these rooms, but generally honeymoon resorts aren’t the place where you want an audience. When the man (it’s almost always the man) opens the door, he usually realizes two things: one, that the presence of sunlight has temporarily blinded him, and two, that there is an ACTUAL PERSON standing there with breakfast. He immediately tries to hide his body behind the door.</p>
<p>That’s a pretty smart play, with one flaw: the walls of the place are covered in mirrors. Ain’t no hiding place here, buddy, and I can see that I won’t be getting a tip because YOU HAVE NO PANTS ON.</p>
<p>There are two approaches here: you can do the silent nod, drop off the tray and get out of there as quickly as possible. That’s the route most newbies take, because I mean, it makes sense. Why would you want to hang around and chat? But that’s what the veterans know: the cheerier you are - “GOOOOD MORNING!” - and the longer you linger, the better the chance that you turn the awkward tables on your already uncomfortable hosts. You do this all the time - they don’t. That’s when you gotta do the small talk, asking how their stay has been, whether they’ve used the jacuzzi yet, or just saying how nice it is outside. After a few seconds, you can tell if he’s going to go back upstairs and get some money or not.</p>
<p>The only real risk with lingering is that you get asked to play photographer. Yes. That is a thing. Ok, it’s not a naked thing, but it’s still a thing. Sometimes people want to have their picture taken on the bed, because it’s a round bed and, really, when are you going to be lying in a round bed again? The photo session is high on the discomfort factor, but if you stick it out you almost always get a tip. And you’ve definitely entitled to give the head nod when the couple arrives for dinner that evening. No waving, though. That’s just weird.</p>
<p>Repeat that process 15-20 times a morning for three months and I assure you that approaching complete strangers to talk is nothing, even if you’re asking some pretty personal questions.</p>
<p>That’s the best training. There may be some long-term side effects.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2018/04/05/the-best-training/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 05 Apr 2018 01:20:05 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Academy Fight Song, Part 2</title>
  <dc:creator>Derek Willis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2017/12/28/academy-fight-song-part-2/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>It begins, as so many things do these days, with a <a href="https://twitter.com/jmart181/status/943316917019955201">tweet</a>.</p>
<p>The tweet references <a href="https://ejobs.umd.edu/postings/55483">an academic job listing</a> from the University of Maryland, where I have taught journalism as an adjunct, and the eye-rolling reactions of professional journalists to it. Like many job listings in the past few years, it has just the right level of “Computer Jesus” in its minimum (!) qualifications:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The successful candidate will have a passion for journalism and the watchdog role it should play in a democratic society. Research and teaching topics of interest to both schools include data analytics as applied to journalism and/or social media; fairness, accountability and transparency in algorithms; news automation; audience analytics and engagement, including those illuminating trends in politics, society or sports; data visualization; social networks; and/or digital innovation. The successful candidate will be expected to have a Ph.D.&nbsp;at the time of appointment.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Now, let’s get something out of the way: there are indeed academics who are qualified for this job, and presumably one of them will be hired to do it. My belief that the population of qualified candidates with <em>substantial journalism experience</em> is relatively small may be mistaken; I’d love to see evidence otherwise.</p>
<p>Back to the tweet by <a href="https://communication.depaul.edu/faculty-and-staff/faculty/Pages/martin2.aspx">Jason Martin</a>, who chairs DePaul’s journalism program and previously worked as a reporter. <a href="https://twitter.com/jmart181/status/943316917019955201">Martin’s claim</a> is about how many professionals view their academic counterparts with disdain, to the extent that we think about them at all. That’s a real thing, although I don’t think that’s what motivated my colleagues’ reactions. As a journalist who has taught at the university level for more than 15 years, I think the reason that some of my colleagues who do work in data journalism engaged in the Twitter eye-rolling is pretty clear: the bulk of the most relevant work being done in these areas is being done in newsrooms by professional journalists. Most of them will only ever teach as an adjunct and, despite the efforts of good administrators, are rarely accepted as anything but temporary necessities by traditional faculty.</p>
<p>So, when we hear this: “Professionals fail to recognize the ways our research informs &amp; enhances industry.”</p>
<p>We also hear this: “We need working professionals to teach many of our advanced skills-based classes that we tell students keep us on the cutting edge, but they will never be considered full participants in higher education unless they have credentials we recognize.”</p>
<p>You would roll your eyes, too.</p>
<p>/////</p>
<p>There is no good reason why the study of what used to be called “computer-assisted reporting” and its descendants has languished in relative obscurity at many universities. If you’re looking for academic work on this area, you could start with <a href="http://www.unc.edu/~pmeyer/">Phil Meyer</a>, who practiced journalism using social science methods and then continued his work in academia.</p>
<p>Here’s <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20070428083511/http://www.asne.org/kiosk/editor/september/meyer.htm">what Meyer wrote in 1996 about journalism education</a>:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Engineering, medicine, business administration, library science - almost any profession you can name that has research committed professional schools has always generated a continuing demand for new knowledge. Every new graduating class from a school of engineering or medicine is viewed nervously by the practitioners in its field because the kids have knowledge that the old guys don’t. Aging engineers wind up in administrative or sales jobs because the technology has changed faster than their ability to keep up.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The sources of that change have been people with research degrees, many of them in universities.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Whether you are ready or not, that is happening to us, even on the craft side. New graduates who can create Web pages, digitize photographs and do electronic searching are in demand precisely because they have skills that midcareer professionals haven’t had the time or interest to acquire. There is also demand for newly trained database reporters who have analytical and statistical skills never learned by their seniors.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The whole thing is worth a read, and then some reflection. It’s not that there aren’t scholars who are examining the use of new technologies or the changes that have overrun journalism in the past 20 years. But Meyer also created and critiqued techniques, like <a href="http://www.academia.edu/860996/The_USA_Today_index_of_ethnic_diversity">The USA TODAY Diversity Index</a> he and Shawn McIntosh, then at the news organization, invented in 1991. His work has been deeply relevant to how we think about journalism but also how we practice it. That’s a big reason why professional journalists doing data-related work hold Meyer in such high esteem.</p>
<p>The sad part is that Meyer could just as easily have published his essay in 2000, 2004, 2008, 2012 or even 2017. Journalism education has not remained exactly the same as it was in 1996 - there are more classes in different areas, including quantitative skills - but these changes have not been broad-based nor have they substantially changed the composition of faculties. Are journalism schools producing the kinds of research now that are guiding newsrooms? Having taught at seven different universities during the past 15 years, my impression is that journalism graduates are more <em>educated</em> and have been exposed to new techniques and technologies, although not in the depth needed. I also believe that the driver of this growth has been the work of industry, not academia. As an aging professional, I worry about graduating kids from other fields more than I do those graduating from most journalism schools.</p>
<p>Advanced degrees, which could be providing the fuel for pushing our field forward, are instead viewed either as necessary credentials just to enter the profession or as a pathway to teaching and research that too often does not address what is happening in the profession, particularly when it comes to the use of quantitative methods.</p>
<p>There are, of course, journalism programs that do a better job of teaching data courses: hiring full-time faculty and even making them eligible for tenure, or offering multiple classes instead of one. But overall the picture is not encouraging. In their 2016 report, <a href="https://journalism.columbia.edu/system/files/content/teaching_data_and_computational_journalism.pdf">“Teaching Data and Computational Journalism”</a>, Charles Berret and Cheryl Phillips surveyed more than 100 journalism programs from the United States and found that “many journalism programs do not have a faculty member skilled in data journalism” and nearly half offer no classes at all. Most are taught by professionals working as adjuncts.</p>
<p>Martin <a href="https://twitter.com/jmart181/status/943327660062724096">suggests</a> that this need not be the case: “And let’s be blunt: good quant PhDs with journalism experience can teach data journalism.” Nobody denies that this is the case, but I’d like to see a list of good quant PhDs with journalism experience currently employed by universities. Is the academy producing enough of them to take over the instruction of data analysis from professionals? If not, is there any expectation of when that might be the case? Are the incentives even in place for this to happen?</p>
<p>Universities that want to serve student needs when it comes to data and digital skills and practices cannot say they are doing it well if they off-load that responsibility to adjuncts teaching upper-level electives or as part of graduate programs that can be prohibitively expensive. Every time I teach, I hear from graduating seniors that they wished they had had <em>any</em> exposure to these types of classes in the past four years - and these are students from R1 research institutions with well-known journalism programs.</p>
<p>The report offers multiple suggestions for changing this situation – all of them useful – but there is a more fundamental issue at play here, the one that Martin’s tweet raises: if there are loads of benefits to journalism that accrue from the work of journalism PhDs, why do many professional journalists think otherwise? What can be done about that? And are universities willing to take those steps?</p>
<p>It’s instructive to look at <a href="https://twitter.com/jmart181/status/943708060643676160">Martin’s response</a> to a question about why a PhD requirement was necessary for that Maryland job:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Produce research that contributes to development/reputation of dept/college &amp; field. Research lines such as gig in question are expected to create publications thru rigor, peer review. Universities have standards for research productivity &amp; evaluate faculty across disciplines.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>All of these benefit the university, the college/department and the researcher, perhaps in that order. If the research itself has benefits for the industry or teaching, how are those valued? Professionals can rightly look at this situation and think: how does this job benefit the aspect of journalism education most visible to them - the education of future journalists and the study of their craft? These aren’t trolling questions. Professional journalists want to increase the skills of journalism students and the number of them who can do quantitative work. We wouldn’t essentially volunteer our time teaching if we didn’t.</p>
<p>I think there are at least two areas that we need to address. The first is to have academics make their research more accessible (both in terms of relevance and availability) and the second is for professionals to have a way to participate in the conversation about that research in a manner that promotes respect and allows industry concerns to inform academic research.</p>
<p>To do both, we could look to political science, where quantitative methods are blossoming along with an ethos that encourages the sharing of data and research. In early January I’ll be attending the <a href="http://spsa.net/">Southern Political Science Association</a> conference, mostly because it has the academic work that is most relevant to my own professional interests of politics and elections (also, it’s in New Orleans). The work of the people I go to see is very much grounded in academic tradition; it also often speaks directly to current issues and events. I get both story ideas and new ways of thinking about how we are doing (or not doing) our job from this conference, and I can recognize the potential uses for journalism. And increasingly, it’s <a href="https://dataverse.harvard.edu/">easier</a> to get at their data. The potential impacts of quantitative political science research have not been <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2014/10/29/upshot/professors-research-project-stirs-political-outrage-in-montana.html?_r=0">without controversy</a>, but from a professional perspective these are conversations we need to be having. And political science has done a <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/monkey-cage/">better job</a> lately of trying to make its research <a href="https://www.vox.com/mischiefs-of-faction">more digestible for general audiences</a>, which communication scholars could use as a basis for experimentation.</p>
<p>In contrast, the <em>theme</em> of the 2017 Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication <a href="http://aejmc.org/events/chicago17/about/">conference</a> was “Closing the Gap: Media, Research and the Profession.” <a href="https://guidebook.com/guide/97687/event/16164480/">Here’s the nut</a>: “Professionals no longer need some of the skills taught in our classes, and, too often, research conducted by educators is no longer relevant to a rapidly evolving industry.” Better sharing would help combat this, and it starts small. Journalism academics should insist on publishing their research instead of having faculty bio pages that contain literally no links to their work, <a href="https://communication.depaul.edu/faculty-and-staff/faculty/Pages/martin2.aspx">Dr.&nbsp;Martin</a>. More <a href="https://github.com/mwe400/IJOCNewsOnEarlyWeb">GitHub repositories</a>, more open sharing of work, please. “We’d like to share our research about mass communication but are prevented by publishing agreements” is another classic eye-roller, even if it’s not something within the complete control of academics. Professionals are <a href="https://github.com/datadesk">figuring this out</a>; it’s time academics join us so that they can dispel our weaker (or non-existent) criticism.</p>
<p>The next necessary step to reduce the disconnect that Martin cites is to get more journalists and academics talking about each other’s work. Nikki Usher, a George Washington University professor, graciously (particularly considering <a href="http://thescoop.org/archives/2012/05/13/lost-in-the-weeds/">my reaction</a> to our initial encounter) offered to organize such a session last year when I was <a href="https://github.com/dwillis/systems-for-reporting">teaching</a> at GW’s School of Media and Public Affairs. <a href="https://twitter.com/nikkiusher/status/943479839784423424">Her description of the session</a> is accurate; I’d only add that I don’t look to academics to develop literal tools for use in the newsroom but to <em>evaluate</em> what we’re doing in a way that we often can’t do. Some of the ideas I offered up include things that probably do sound trivial or boring to researchers, but as newsrooms are literally redefining their structures and operations, even measuring the outputs would help advance our understanding of the craft. These conversations will be awkward or even uncomfortable at times; they are all the more necessary for it. Prof.&nbsp;Usher’s has <a href="https://medium.com/@nikkiusher/does-anyone-care-about-journalism-research-no-really-358d789b749a">thoughts on this process that are worth reading</a>, although in some cases I think she answers glib questions with glib answers.</p>
<p>I am not anti-academic. I saw the frustrations my dad dealt with in achieving his PhD and securing a university job that expected published research. My own undergraduate education was more theoretical (<a href="https://theconversation.com/defending-science-how-the-art-of-rhetoric-can-help-68210">rhetoric!</a>) than practical, and the time I have spent teaching has been some of the most rewarding of my career. But I am increasingly concerned that the imbalance between professionals and the academy, in which both of us retreat to our corners and snipe at the other, is not only corrosive to both but poses a larger threat to journalism education. I’m not sure that data journalism is best taught in an academic setting, that the existing incentives and structures offer few rewards for those who try and serve students and industry poorly. I think that segment of journalism education could actually be done better outside the university setting, which would be problematic for schools trying to attract students. Mostly, I’m not sure how much more I want to participate in a system that takes our energy and time but isn’t interested in supporting work that isn’t connected to a PhD, as <a href="https://twitter.com/SStirling/status/943667810567360514">Stephen Stirling puts it so well</a>.</p>
<p>If we want to bridge this gap, maybe what’s necessary is for professionals who teach data-related classes to teach <em>less</em> and to focus more on discussing research and advising both journalism schools and student journalists. I serve on councils for the <a href="https://www.jou.ufl.edu/">University of Florida</a> and <a href="https://mediainnovation.wvu.edu/">West Virginia University</a>, and perhaps that is where I can make more of a difference, along with trying to serve as a mentor for individual students and young professionals. The hard reality is that my teaching experience has increased the disconnect between my own work and the academic institutions that prepare students for it, not helped to narrow it. We all lose when that gap persists, but students lose the most, and in the end we will all pay for it.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2017/12/28/academy-fight-song-part-2/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2017 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Government and Civic Tech</title>
  <dc:creator>Derek Willis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2016/09/29/government-and-civic-tech/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Looking at what has happened to civic technology organizations at the national level lately, you could get the impression that the federal government, having absorbed some of the lessons of organizations like the <a href="http://sunlightfoundation.com/blog/2016/09/20/statement-from-sunlight-foundations-board-chairman/">Sunlight Foundation</a> and <a href="http://civichall.org/civicist/recharging-the-brigade-code-for-americas-challenge/">Code for America</a>, has pulled energy and talent away from those entities, making it harder for them to exist.</p>
<p>I think there is some truth to this, but it is not nearly the whole story and we risk drawing the wrong lessons from it. In general, I subscribe to <a href="https://medium.com/@joshuatauberer/civic-techs-act-iii-is-beginning-4df5d1720468#.f22421fan">what Josh Tauberer says on this</a>, but I think it’s worth exploring what it means after this migration from civic organizations into government.</p>
<p>The flow of people from civic technology groups (and those in similar orbits, like journalism) into government service is, in once sense, part of a progression. Organizations like Sunlight have done some of the work they argue that government should be doing: making data more easily available and creating user experiences that citizens might actually find useful. It makes sense that governments do that where appropriate, and to some extent that could impact Sunlight’s ability to raise money to do similar work.</p>
<p>I am not convinced that government technologists are doing the same work, however, or that, as <a href="http://krues8dr.com/blog/2016/09/27/the-end-of-the-second-act-of-civic-tech/">Bill Hunt writes</a>, such efforts are “seemingly bypassing the need for civic tech entirely.” Labeling that kind of work as civic tech is accurate only up to a point. Instead, I’d offer “government tech” as a more fitting description of the work being done. This makes sense: if the federal government hires technologists, it stands to reason that they would work on government technology issues and problems. The examples of 18F and the U.S. Digital Service show that, given the resources, government technologists will tackle government problems like <a href="https://github.com/18F/micropurchase">procurement</a>, <a href="https://github.com/18F/web-design-standards">design</a> and <a href="https://github.com/18F/hhs-acf-uc-dashboard">data integration</a>.</p>
<p>There are some exceptions to this – I am still impressed and somewhat surprised that 18F has been working on an <a href="https://github.com/18F/openFEC">API for the Federal Election Commission’s data</a>, for example – but as a taxpayer I would expect that government technologists work on the many issues and opportunities their situations present. One could reasonably argue that there is a civic component of this, and to a point that’s true. But I do not think it is identical to the mission and purpose of organizations such as Sunlight or to the work of individuals like <a href="https://razor.occams.info/">Josh Tauberer</a>. Parallel at times, sure.</p>
<p>Think of it this way: if Congress ever decided to do something like 18F or USDS, an obvious project would be adding voting data to Congress.gov. But there’s a reason that <a href="https://www.congress.gov/">Congress.gov</a>, as fine as it is, doesn’t show recent votes by lawmakers or offer users the ability to compare voting records: it serves no <strong>government</strong> purpose to do so. Comparing voting records, or seeing how often your representative misses votes, are civic tasks: they are designed to benefit citizens, regardless of the wishes of elected officials. That’s one reason people like <a href="https://www.govtrack.us/">GovTrack</a>: it tells them things they want to know about their representatives that those representatives have little incentive to provide.</p>
<p>The barriers to providing such information have never been technical, not really. When Josh and others were asking the Library of Congress for bulk legislative data 10 years ago, it wasn’t as if the technical capacity to make it happen didn’t exist. The reasons given for it not happening were entirely political.</p>
<p>That doesn’t mean that government technology work has little or no civic benefit: plenty of it clearly does, and my friends who work in agencies in desperate need of their talent are doing this for all of us. As a taxpayer and someone who works with technology, I value that work and I hope it continues.</p>
<p>But it might not, for a couple of reasons. Funding for government programs can end, some of these jobs are explicitly temporary and many of the people attracted to government service in this area have skills that are worth far more in the private sector. If you are hired into the federal government near or at a <a href="https://www.opm.gov/policy-data-oversight/pay-leave/salaries-wages/salary-tables/pdf/2016/GS.pdf">GS-15 level</a>, there is little room for you to earn more. Some could choose to stay, for good reasons.</p>
<p>Some of the people who joined 18F and USDS will go back to the private sector, and we’ve got some for-profit efforts that do similar work in the civic space, too. That’s not a bad thing; it validates the idea that information can be powerful and useful. I don’t begrudge people making money from public information (well, maybe I do if they are government employees themselves), but as with government work, it’s not exactly the same work as what Dan O’Neil and his <a href="http://www.derivativeworks.com/2016/05/leaving-smart-chicago-for-ad-hoc.html">former colleagues at Smart Chicago Collaborative</a> have been doing. That stuff is hard.</p>
<p>Institutions and programs come and go. What remains is the need for focused work that makes it easier for citizens to understand what their governments are doing with their money and in their name. Some of that can be done by government. Some of that can be done by the private sector. But some of it - the less popular stuff that can’t be easily monetized or takes a lot of effort to do - won’t ever happen without dedicated people who work outside those two sectors. That’s part of what made the idea of Sunlight Labs, even if it didn’t always deliver the goods, so necessary.</p>
<p>I agree that we largely are past the days of foundations throwing millions of dollars at individual tools and platforms that marry technology with a civic purpose (and here I should say that a project of mine, <a href="http://www.openelections.net/">OpenElections</a>, got <a href="http://www.knightfoundation.org/press/releases/six-ventures-bring-data-public-winners-knight-news">$200,000 from the Knight Foundation</a>, which was a huge help). That’s probably a good thing in some respects, because it led to a surplus of similarly-oriented projects that all required maintenance. We’ve seen the result of that: consolidation or elimination, <a href="https://theunitedstates.io/">hopefully preserving</a> the best ideas and practices. If funders want to see a different focus, or more explicit outcomes, the people working in this area need to respond to that or find another way to do what they want to do.</p>
<p>It may be frustrating to everyone in this space that we are still working on the infrastructure of civic information, but there is so much work to be done, and there is clear evidence that building such platforms can make it easier for others to create <a href="https://dssg.uchicago.edu/2015/07/09/sunlight-project-finding-legislative-plagiarism/">meaningful things</a> that put more power in the hands of citizens. Let’s keep doing that however we can, trying to avoid the mistakes we’ve all made, and not forget that people, and not institutions, are why we do this.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2016/09/29/government-and-civic-tech/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2016 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>My Favorite Things</title>
  <dc:creator>Derek Willis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2015/07/29/my-favorite-things/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>As first reported on the tweets, <a href="https://www.propublica.org/about/derek-willis-to-join-propublicas-politics-team">I have a new job</a>, at ProPublica, where I’ll be working on news applications, investigations and other incredible stuff with the <a href="https://www.propublica.org/data/">News Apps team</a>.</p>
<p>Leaving The New York Times wasn’t easy. There are so many good people there, so many really smart journalists. So as a way of saying goodbye, here’s a list of some of my favorite things from my seven-and-a-half years at The Times (my longest time in any job, btw):</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="http://projects.nytimes.com/represent/">Represent</a>. Even though it didn’t last, this was the most rewarding thing I worked on in terms of coming up with an idea and seeing it to <a href="http://open.blogs.nytimes.com/2008/12/22/represent/">completion</a>, thanks mostly to my then-colleague Andrei Scheinkman, now at FiveThirtyEight. Represent was a departure for The Times into personalization and feed aggregation at a time when both were still new ideas in the newsroom. It also was, to the best of my knowledge, the first Django app at the NYT. We stopped maintaining it a few years ago, but it lived on in other projects, including the <a href="http://developer.nytimes.com/docs/read/districts_api">Districts API</a> and “<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/nyregion/The-Other-Races.html">The Other Races</a>” from 2013.</li>
<li><a href="http://projects.nytimes.com/toxic-waters">Toxic Waters</a>. One of the first large projects I worked on at The Times, this involved both obtaining and loading EPA data as well as helping to decide how we’d present records of inspections and violations for water pollution permit holders. I didn’t do the really amazing visual aspects of this project, but really enjoyed digging into a new dataset and being able to help readers find out more information on water pollution where they live.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/nytimes/Fech">Fech</a>. This started as an intern project with Michael Strickland and Evan Carmi; the goal was to create an internal toolkit to process electronic campaign finance filings from the FEC. Since <a href="http://open.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/08/29/introducing-fech/">releasing it</a>, we’ve gotten contributions from people outside The Times and Fech has become something of a standard, inspiring a Python version, too. It also powers <a href="http://itemizer.herokuapp.com/">Itemizer</a>.</li>
<li><a href="http://elections.nytimes.com/2012/">2012 Election Coverage and results</a>. Elections are a huge deal at The Times, an all-hands-on-deck affair. I was really proud to be a part of the process for elections beginning in 2008, but for me 2012 was a high-water mark. We were able to build individual campaign finance elements like <a href="http://elections.nytimes.com/2012/campaign-finance">this one with Jeremy Ashkenas</a> and <a href="http://elections.nytimes.com/2012/campaign-finance/independent-expenditures/totals">another with Kevin Quealy</a>, plus contribute to <a href="http://elections.nytimes.com/2012/results/president/exit-polls">exit polls</a> and other parts.</li>
<li><a href="http://developer.nytimes.com/docs/campaign_finance_api/">Campaign Finance</a> and <a href="http://developer.nytimes.com/docs/congress_api">Congress</a> APIs. These were somewhat accidental projects in the sense that from a publishing standpoint they weren’t strictly necessary. But both APIs provided information to the public that otherwise would have been difficult to obtain. Even though the FEC now has an API and the United States project has expanded the congressional data available, they have been used in <a href="http://finzi.psych.upenn.edu/library/govdat/html/nyt_cg_membersponsorcompare.html">academic projects</a>, <a href="http://danwin.com/2012/01/congressmiles-a-ruby-coding-tutorial-with-the-face-and-times-congress-apis/">silly projects</a> and <a href="https://projects.propublica.org/sandyvote/">serious projects</a>.</li>
<li>Upshot Mississippi Senate primary coverage. The 2014 GOP primary and runoff in Mississippi gave me a chance to use precinct-level results data in near real-time. Pairing with Nate Cohn, we examined the impact of black turnout in <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/07/10/upshot/voting-totals-reveal-crucial-boost-from-blacks-in-cochrans-victory.html">two</a> <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/07/15/upshot/more-evidence-that-thad-cochran-owes-runoff-win-to-black-voters.html">stories</a> that provided evidence instead of just anecdotes. I also was able to delve into the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/06/17/upshot/a-church-pac-link-raises-questions-in-mississippi.html">murky world of outside spending in that race</a>.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/05/07/upshot/a-mysterious-republican-committee-in-the-virgin-islands.html">VIGOP</a> This is a crazy story, still ongoing, about how a small party organization is trying to raise its profile through some controversial and fairly unorthodox methods. The artwork makes it even better.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/09/06/upshot/looking-for-john-mccain-try-a-sunday-morning-show.html">Sunday Morning Talk Show Guests</a>. One of my favorite things to do is to try and confirm or debunk the conventional wisdom about a topic, and there are few things more conventional wisdom than being a guest on the Sunday talk shows. I worked for several weeks standardizing data on talk show guests (<a href="https://github.com/TheUpshot/Sunday-Shows">which we released</a>) and then <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2014/09/05/upshot/05up-sundayguests.html">helped build the table</a> that displayed the most frequent guests.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/10/09/upshot/how-actblue-became-a-powerful-force-in-fund-raising.html">ActBlue</a>. One of the biggest stories around political fundraising has been the rise of the small donor, and ActBlue, a Democratic conduit organization, is right in the middle of that. I used ActBlue filings to show how their users have expanded and grown as repeat donors, to the benefit of Democratic candidates and organizations up and down the ballot.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/06/28/upshot/maiden-names-on-the-rise-again.html">Maiden Names</a>. When I came to The Times, I half-jokingly said that one of my goals was to combine the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/pages/fashion/weddings/index.html">wedding announcements</a> with people mentioned in <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/pages/business/dealbook/index.html">DealBook</a> to create a network of New York’s elite. We never did that, but before I left I was able to finally do an analysis of wedding announcement data with my Upshot colleague Claire Cain Miller and get a Sunday Styles byline, to boot. This one was a lot of fun, and a great way to end my time at The Times.</li>
</ol>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2015/07/29/my-favorite-things/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2015 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Civic Data and Journalism</title>
  <dc:creator>Derek Willis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2015/06/06/civic-data-and-journalism/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>A solid foundation of publicly available, consistent civic data - think of election results, voting information and other political records - is more important than ever for journalism. And while we’ve made a good start, we have a long way to go.</p>
<p>On June 5 I had the privilege of being on a panel at the <a href="https://personaldemocracy.com/static-content/pdf-2015-program">Personal Democracy Forum</a> in New York with Luciana Lopez of Reuters, Jonathan Capehart of The Washington Post and Jenn Topper of the Sunlight Foundation. The title was “How Civic Tech is Changing the Way Newsrooms Cover Elections,” and our discussion was wide-ranging, thanks to a) good panel selection and b) expansive definitions of civic tech.</p>
<p>My basic theme was this: newsrooms need access to a basic level of civic data and technology now more than ever, for two major reasons. First, the days when most newsrooms had the budget and staff to maintain their own versions of important civic data (like voter files or campaign contributions) are gone. Instead, the most common options are seeking out such data from third-party providers or not doing it at all. While there are some excellent third-party providers, including the folks at Sunlight and the Center for Responsive Politics, this is still a system that makes it harder for journalists to stumble across potential stories on their own.</p>
<p>Second, consensus on how to describe some political situation is harder to achieve when the number of publishers multiplies. Maybe we don’t want total consensus, but I’d argue that it’s desirable and important that we at least are able to have a common understanding of the key data that informs our civic life and how we report on it. Along with methodological transparency, it’s a way that we can be upfront with readers and each other.</p>
<p>Two projects have helped make these points clearer to me. The first, <a href="https://theunitedstates.io/">the United States project</a>, is the result of conversations between Eric Mill (then at Sunlight), Joshua Tauberer of Govtrack and myself that came to a head in August 2012. We all agreed that it made no sense for each of us to maintain separate scrapers for legislative data, and that beyond duplicative work, it created the possibility that different choices made in isolation would result in different data. No one wanted a situation in which three providers of congressional data disagreed with each other - and we had a few cases of that, inadvertently.</p>
<p>The project grew from an initial focus on Congress to include executive branch data, including <a href="https://github.com/unitedstates/inspectors-general">a central repository of inspector general reports</a>. It now has a number of contributors, and decisions are made by rough consensus. The result is a stable foundation of legislative data. If, for example, <a href="http://developer.nytimes.com/docs/congress_api">The New York Times Congress API</a> that I maintain were to be discontinued, something very similar to it could be re-created in a matter of weeks, if not days, using this data as its primary source. In less than three years, a group of volunteers has made it possible for virtually anyone seeking bulk legislative data to not have to spend weeks or months reinventing the wheel. That’s a huge accomplishment for civic technology, and for journalism.</p>
<p>The second project is <a href="http://openelections.net/">OpenElections</a>, which I’ve been working on along with Serdar Tumgoren and a host of volunteers since early 2013. This effort will go on for years, but its goal is to remove the high barriers to journalists and developers seeking to work with historic election results data. To make it easier for people to understand how elections have played out in their towns, counties and states over the past 15 years (and further if we can). Most newsrooms, never bastions of efficiency during good economic times, now face pressures that make it all but impossible to embark on months-long efforts to collect and parse data. If they were able to do so, OpenElections wouldn’t exist.</p>
<p>What makes these efforts worthwhile for me is the idea that someone, somewhere will use the data we’ve gathered and published to make something I’ve never considered. Or to look at issues or trends I’ll never look at. This is public data; it should have a public home and a public understanding. There’s still a huge role for journalism in civic technology, none bigger than providing context and understanding from our shared foundation. And there’s still a lot of work to do. We have too many silos of civic information about politicians and candidates. We duplicate each other’s work too often to make sense.</p>
<p>The United States project and OpenElections could have been owned by a single newsroom and turned out ok. But I don’t think that’s the best scenario, because then the data that provides a common foundation is subject to a single organization’s control. We literally, and figuratively, can’t afford that.</p>
<p>So here’s what you can do: if you’re interested in congressional or election results data, consider contributing to these projects. Or consider filling the other gaps we have, especially at lower levels of government. But whatever you do, try to ensure that your work doesn’t become someone else’s repetition. Our common foundation, and our ability to deliver the kind of journalism that our civic life demands, can’t afford it, either.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2015/06/06/civic-data-and-journalism/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jun 2015 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>We’re All Publishers Now</title>
  <dc:creator>Derek Willis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2014/11/17/were-all-publishers-now/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Last weekend I had myself a proper Twitter rant.</p>
<p>It began with <a href="https://twitter.com/derekwillis/status/533778178658279424">this</a>: “We need to talk about newsroom efficiency, a phrase right up there with ‘cruel kindness’ or ‘deafening silence’ in its oxymoronic quality.”</p>
<p>Newsroom efficiency is a <a href="http://thescoop.org/thefix/">little bit of a white whale for me</a>. I know most newsrooms can never be made completely efficient, nor should they, for the kinds of inspiration needed for doing journalism isn’t available in predictable forms. I have no illusions about the messiness of what we do.</p>
<p>There was a time when efficiency didn’t matter as much, or even much at all. Our timeframes were elongated, not compressed. Our budgets were fat, not lean. Perhaps most important, the duties of reporting and editing the news were tied to its production process only by a printing and delivery schedule. If the presses stopped working, there was very little reporters could do about it. Production - publishing - was someone else’s problem.</p>
<p>Those days are slipping away fast.</p>
<p>Virtually every journalist today is closer to the tools of publishing the news than at any point since the <a href="http://www.history.org/Almanack/life/trades/tradepri.cfm">hand-pulled press</a> of colonial times. We can push buttons and our words, images and graphics appear on the Web. A story’s afterlife - what happens when it has been published - is something that we can revise and extend. These are hugely important changes; they alter what is possible for all of us.</p>
<p>Too many of us ignore or downplay this. We don’t know the means of production, and don’t want to know. It’ll get done by someone, right? That much is true - if we continue to be detached from the tools that publish our journalism, it will get done by someone else. It’s just that that someone is likely to be literally someone else.</p>
<p>We cannot remain strangers to the means of publishing. In other words: for your own sake and that of your co-workers, learn to use your CMS.</p>
<p>(I’ll pause here for an obligatory eye-rolling.)</p>
<p>Yes, the CMS. The software we love to complain about, the deleter of edits, the thing that crashes when you can least afford it. To the extent that reporters and editors think about their CMSes beyond epithets, it usually involves something like <a href="http://curiousontheroad.com/2011/12/from-journalist-to-programmer-give-us-better-a-cms/">this</a>: “If I could make one Christmas wish to developers, it would be for a better content management system.”</p>
<p>Well, you can’t spell “better content management system” without “you.” I mean, you <em>can</em>, but not in practice. Reporters and editors need to be better, stronger users of their publishing tools, not just to be effective at their jobs but to shape and inform the growth and improvement of those tools. You can summon all the developers you want, but if you don’t actually use what they build, they won’t know how to make something useful for you.</p>
<p>I’ve had to use a number of CMSes in my career, and very few of them could fairly be called “great.” But even the worst ones - the ones I dreaded opening and tried to avoid - contained surprisingly useful features. If you, as a user, participate in the development of your CMS, you’re gonna end up with a more useful CMS. If you don’t, you’re holding yourself and possibly your colleagues back.</p>
<p>You might ask why this matters so much. Who cares if I file a story using email, Word or Google Docs rather than my CMS? Here’s why: unlike publishing systems of the past, the modern CMS publishes directly to the Web. That means that you are a publisher. And that means that you can become a better publisher, knowing how to add links, where to place photographs or graphics, or how something will look to a reader on a phone.</p>
<p>Perhaps you didn’t sign up for this. You wanted to be a writer, an editor, a photographer, a graphics editor. And you can be. Now you’re also a publisher, too, and the longer we shrink from that responsibility, the more problems we’ll all have.</p>
<p>No CMS is perfect. That’s why we need to use them, so we can help shape them and use them to put our best journalism in front of our readers and know how they are reading it. Choosing not to use your CMS is choosing not to be a part of that process, and unlike the past, when someone else did the publishing for all of us, it’s our responsibility.</p>
<p>Not everyone will become a power user. Not everyone needs to: any piece of software with a reasonably broad set of users will need to accomodate them. But if you never know how it works, you’ll never be able to make it better for yourself, your organization and ultimately your readers. You can’t be a tourist visting your own workflow.</p>
<p>Here’s what you can do: start using your CMS if you don’t. Then, find out who works on it and tell them what you like and don’t like. Chances are they would love to hear this kind of feedback. Ask questions: Why can’t I do this? Would it be possible to do this other thing?</p>
<p>I started this rant with “newsroom efficiency.” Here’s how that factors in. Right now, the people who don’t use the CMS are being supported by people who are doing that for them: they are copying and pasting, clicking buttons on a story that isn’t theirs and will never be as important to them as it is to its creators. Imagine what they could be doing, the work they could be creating, if they didn’t have to do this. Maybe they would think of a new way to tell stories online. Maybe they’d have the room for that inspiration to strike, the kind that leads to amazing stories.</p>
<p>But this isn’t a zero-sum game. You’ll be better off, too, having more control over what you publish and a bigger role in building our future. You’re a publisher now.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2014/11/17/were-all-publishers-now/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2014 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Lightning Strikes</title>
  <dc:creator>Derek Willis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2014/07/08/lightning-strikes/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>On November 19, 2009, Jaimi Dowdell of Investigative Reporters &amp; Editors sent an email to more than a dozen of us asking about some ideas for advanced sessions for the <a href="http://www.ire.org/blog/ire-news/2009/06/30/asus-cronkite-school-will-host-2010-car-confere/">2010 CAR conference in Phoenix</a>. Here’s part of my response:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I think the ideas are great. A couple of possible suggestions:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>A session of “lightning talks”, in which people present a single idea or technique in a short time. I think it would lessen the pressure on presenters and expand the universe of them, too. http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lightning_Talk</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<p>Every once in awhile, I have an idea that pans out.</p>
<p>Lightning talks, a popular feature of many a conference, were almost completely unknown to the journalism community. A few of us had seen them at technical conferences we’d been to, but mostly it was a foreign concept, particularly for a conference that had always featured 45-minute sessions with talks by the very best data reporters and editors around.</p>
<p>The first session in Phoenix was in a pretty standard room. There were 10 talks that year, and half of the audience consisted of the presenters. Here’s the lineup:</p>
<ul>
<li>Google Charts. Easy, Clear, Indestructable. (Ben Welsh)</li>
<li>Like Snowboard Cross, but With Data (Scott Klein)</li>
<li>The new free visualization tool (Sarah Cohen)</li>
<li>Easy peasy due diligence (Danielle Cervantes)</li>
<li>Data Manipulation or Graphics with R (Bill Alpert)</li>
<li>Essential Queries for SQL Server (Anthony DeBarros)</li>
<li>Using an API with Excel (Derek Willis)</li>
<li>Easy interactive charts with Open Flash Charts (Tim Henderson)</li>
<li>Hello, Newsroom! Build out a GIS-enabled web app in &lt; five minutes (Brian Boyer)</li>
<li>The hidden power of Javascript (Michelle Minkoff)</li>
</ul>
<p>Picking Ben Welsh to lead off was, in hindsight, a rookie mistake on my part, but the session was pretty well-received, and we all had fun doing it (all 25-30 of us). Fast forward to earlier this year, and here was the crowd for the lightning talks in Baltimore:</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<figure class="figure">
<img src="https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2014/07/08/lightning-strikes/http:/knightlab.northwestern.edu/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/lightningtalks_NICAR14_akesslerdc.jpg" title="Holy crap!" class="img-fluid figure-img">
</figure>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">A big crowd</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In five years, lightning talks went from being a small session competing with other sessions for attendees to a <a href="http://ire.org/conferences/nicar-2014/lightning/">standing-room only event</a> in the biggest ballroom the hotel had. I’ve been privileged to help run it, along with Aron Pilhofer and the folks at IRE who constantly encouraged and supported it. My favorite part of the last few NICAR conferences has been seeing new speakers (and some regulars) wow and entertain their colleagues.</p>
<p>And that’s why it’s time for me to hand over the lightning talk reins: because we have so much talent in our community, and five years is long enough for anyone to be heading up a showcase of our brightest. Starting this summer, Sisi Wei, who gave a remarkable talk in 2013 about <a href="http://vimeo.com/61297159">making games for news</a>, will be leading the session at next year’s conference in Atlanta. Besides being a smart and funny and good person, Sisi is also someone who has worked very hard to bring new people into our community, and that’s one reason she’s such a good person to lead lightning talks.</p>
<p>We’ve already talked in general about some of the changes that lightning talks needs now that it’s such a popular event. Mainly, these changes involve the talk submission and voting process, which in the past has favored people who pitched earliest and those who are well-known in our community. We’ve grown too much for that to continue. For many first-time NICAR attendees, lightning talks are perhaps the one place where they could see themselves being able to contribute; after all, it’s just five minutes as opposed to an hour. Working with the IRE staff, Sisi will be mindful of the need for lightning talks to be a place where we get to hear from a broad range of speakers with different levels of experience. It might also be time to retire the <a href="http://ire.aronpilhofer.com">submission site</a> that Aron hastily put together years ago.</p>
<p>None of this would be possible were it not for the openness of IRE, including Mark Horvit, who has been incredibly supportive of lightning talks, and of the IRE staff. All of us owe a debt to them and to that first round of speakers who tried something new, and made it a success.</p>
<p>Witnessing the growth of lightning talks at NICAR has been a joy for me. I have always looked forward to presenting the lineup of awesome presenters and watching as the audience were blown away by their passion and creativity. Now I get to experience that myself, and we all get the benefit that IRE has always provided: dedicated volunteers helping to make our profession that much better. I can’t wait to see what Sisi has for us in Atlanta.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2014/07/08/lightning-strikes/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2014 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="http://knightlab.northwestern.edu/wp-content/uploads/2014/03/lightningtalks_NICAR14_akesslerdc.jpg " medium="image"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How It Starts</title>
  <dc:creator>Derek Willis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2014/05/22/how-it-starts/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Tomorrow is Aron Pilhofer’s last day at The New York Times.</p>
<p>Aron joined The Times in 2005, first working with the computer-assisted reporting desk then headed by Tom Torok. In the summer of 2007, I was working at washingtonpost.com doing things that other newsrooms weren’t doing. And then Aron started talking about this team he would be building at The Times. It was a compelling pitch, even though washingtonpost.com was ahead of the pack. “You should have a blast,” he wrote in one email.</p>
<p>Thanks to Aron, it has been one hell of a ride.</p>
<p>It’s instructive to look back at the beginnings of Interactive News at The Times, when we had five or six people, a charge of developing web applications and literally no infrastructure of our own. Our initial 2008 presidential primary app ran off a Windows box belonging to CAR. One person could “login” to it at a time and if you think that Rails runs slowly on Windows now, you should have seen it then. Sometimes, the Windows box needed to be rebooted by CAR. We used the same user names and passwords because a) there were so few of us and b) it was easier to create one account than five. Which led to emails like this one from Ben Koski in June 2008, during a presidential primary: “Tonight my newsweb password expired promptly at 8pm, perhaps one of the most inopportune moments for a password change.”</p>
<p>We were parasites. We squatted on whatever servers we could get access to, which once resulted in a box we used being literally unplugged and moved to a different data center - a totally scheduled thing - that we were completely unaware of until we tried to ssh to it. The migration took a couple of days. We cooled our jets, and developed a plan where we could publish election results off Ben’s laptop if need be. It was not a frivolous plan; there was a non-zero chance it would be needed.</p>
<p>Aron “acquired” some hardware we could actually see - the late, lamented server he called “jeffvader”. The prototype for <a href="http://www.j-lab.org/about/press-releases/new-york-times-wins-top-knight-batten-award-for-innovations-in-journalism/">Represent</a> first lived on jeffvader. Lots of things lived on jeffvader. We ran <em>Django</em> on jeffvader, for goodness sake. Jeffvader was in use until at least mid-2010.</p>
<p>But Aron kept pushing and pushing for us to get access to Amazon’s cloud offerings, kept pushing for us to have access to ports that were not widely available, pushed to make sure that, whatever the obstacle, we’d figure it out. It was rarely a thing a beauty, but then anyone who makes something new knows that not every day is a work of art.</p>
<p>Once we got access to EC2 servers, we just started spinning them up for stuff. We’d get emails from Aron periodically asking, “Does anyone know what is running on (random Amazon IP address)?” It wasn’t a scolding thing; it was basically housekeeping duties. He was (usually) patient as we all stumbled around in the dark, trying to figure this thing out.</p>
<p>We switched from using Subversion to using Git, saw each other through Rails upgrades, database meltdowns (mostly caused by me) and near-calamities on production servers. Only once did I feel any sort of anxiety from Aron; on election night in 2008, he warmed us up by smiling and saying, basically, “If this doesn’t go right, don’t come in tomorrow.” We had that sort of nervous laughter, but if it had failed - if we had failed - it might have been the end of INT, which was barely a year old. But we didn’t fail.</p>
<p>All of this is worth mentioning not just to recognize what Aron has done at The Times in building Interactive News, but to suggest that this sort of change doesn’t come easily and isn’t handed to you. You have to make a play for it, and that involves sticking your neck out and trusting that your colleagues will do the same. It requires selling everyone - perspective employees, current colleagues and higher-ups - on something that isn’t quite there yet.</p>
<p>None of us knew what we were doing - not in the way we do today, when there are habits and practices and traditions. We had no idea where we might end up. But we had a guide, and we found the way. Thanks, Aron.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2014/05/22/how-it-starts/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2014 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Data Journalism, Student Media Edition</title>
  <dc:creator>Derek Willis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2013/10/09/data-journalism-student-media-edition/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>I had the privilege of <a href="https://twitter.com/dukesanford/status/387608300600426496">speaking to students (and some faculty) at Duke University</a> on Monday, and it was inspiring to see so many people come out to listen to a very geeky talk, to say nothing of the speaker. Afterwards, several students came up to ask how they could start doing data journalism at a student newspaper, particularly at a private university not subject to most public records requests. If I’m going to encourage student journalists to embrace data journalism, it’s only right that I try to provide some suggestions on how to do this in a university environment.</p>
<p>First suggestion: as much as you’d like to address issues of national significance - and I totally did this when I worked at both The Pitt News and The Independent Florida Alligator - stick to what is right in front of you. Universities large and small are communities themselves, with often strange and interesting methods of governance and communication. They make for great stories. With that in mind, start with your university’s <a href="http://ir.provost.duke.edu/">Institutional Research office</a>. It might be called something else, but nearly every school has something like it. The IR office’s job is to collect information - data - about the school, its students and faculty, and to publish reports on the same. IR offices often conduct surveys, too, which can tell you what kinds of questions are important to the university (some even do <a href="http://web.mit.edu/surveys/parent2007/core/welcome.html">surveys of parents</a>).</p>
<p>Some are pretty good about publishing data as data, usually a spreadsheet. Other times it’ll be a <a href="http://ir.provost.duke.edu/facts/tuitionandfinaid/tuition%20history%20through%201213.pdf">PDF</a> or maybe even a Word doc. It doesn’t matter - you’ll want to build your own set of data about the university, and you won’t want to restrict yourself to only what IR offices are interested in. Start with a spreadsheet - maybe Google spreadsheets, so multiple people can access or edit it. Consider this <a href="http://thescoop.org/thefix/the-information-gap/">a resource for your entire news organization</a>, not just you. When you leave, make sure someone else takes over the care and feeding of it. Make it so that your student paper or radio station is an expert in the demographics of the university.</p>
<p>As you build up a collection of data, you’ll be able to write actual trend stories about incoming classes or the number of full-time faculty at the school. Instead of having to recompile the same information over and over for different stories, you can do it once and use it all over the place. And it’s not like the university can say that the data isn’t correct; they can, but they’ll need to correct it.</p>
<p>Second suggestion: Follow the <a href="http://research.duke.edu/">research</a> money. Higher education is now a complex combination of students, faculty, administrators and the funding that makes it all possible. Faculty members hope to bring in research money to pursue their interests and to enhance their profiles. While a not insignificant portion of that research is funded by private sources, the government pays for quite a lot of academic research. Student media outlets should know about it. After all, the <a href="http://www.dukechronicle.com/articles/2013/09/23/duke-professor-wins-award-advance-research">occasional story about a faculty research grant</a> is a common thing for a lot of campus newspapers.</p>
<p>(Note: were the federal government not shutdown at the moment, I’d provide some links to sources of research grant information and data. But you’re journalists, you can find them.)</p>
<p>Third suggestion: Decide what 2-3 things that your university does that makes it regionally or nationally known. This may include athletics. Figure out how to dive deep into those subjects, including collecting whatever data is available. If sports is on the table, then track plays or players or coaches or all of the above. If it’s a particular school or department, gather up all the details on faculty, classes, students, etc. Ask students and faculty what they’d like to know about those things, or what they <em>think</em> they already know. Own your home court, basically. That should be something Duke students, at least, find familiar.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2013/10/09/data-journalism-student-media-edition/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2013 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Natives Aren’t Restless Enough</title>
  <dc:creator>Derek Willis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2013/10/01/the-natives-arent-restless-enough/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>A couple of points to start with, in the hopes of not wasting readers’ time and preparing for some reactions:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>This post could be named “Get Off My Lawn” or “In My Day, We Earned It!” or some other title that would demonstrate that I am, more than ever, a <a href="https://twitter.com/kendall/status/385111992799084544">cranky old guy</a> now.</li>
<li>What follows obviously does not apply to everyone younger than I am (42, for the record). But it does apply to a distressingly large percentage of those who I have taught at the university level (undergraduate and graduate) over the past eight years.</li>
<li>This post stems from one sentence in a <a href="http://www.poynter.org/latest-news/top-stories/223548/online-course-shows-impact-importance-of-data-driven-journalism/">Poynter summary of a MOOC I helped teach</a>, but this is not about the author of that piece. It’s about a larger mindset that I see.</li>
<li>Youth is wasted on the young. (See point #1, above.)</li>
</ol>
<p>This post could be about how slow, feature-less and pathetic the Internet tools and sites I first encountered were compared to the ones we have now, but as we know too well, nostalgia isn’t a selling point. It could be a screed about how kids today don’t appreciate what they have, but I’ve tried that on our seven-year-old daughter with minimal results. Instead, this is about the very real situation I see in classrooms and among too many people who describe themselves as “digitally savvy” or “digital natives”.</p>
<p>I really enjoyed the <a href="https://knightcenter.utexas.edu/node/14149/">data journalism MOOC itself</a> and was glad to see the Poynter write-up. It was my first involvement with MOOCs and it was a fascinating experiment. But there was one line from the Poynter piece that brought to the surface a couple of thoughts I’ve been harboring for awhile about teaching journalism to people who have grown up with the Web. Here it is:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I’m a millennial and therefore digitally savvy, but I could feel sweat bead across my forehead while reading Matt Waite’s account of scraping government data to create Politifact.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The term “digitally savvy” (or, worse, “digital native”) is more flash than substance, but let me take a stab at what it is supposed to refer to: individuals who supposedly emerged from the womb with a facility for computing devices, the Internet and (especially) social media. They speak (type) an abbreviated language mystifying to their elders, have some different theories on the notions of sharing and privacy and have been exposed since an early age to what is surely much more information than any generation in humanity’s existence.</p>
<p>Let’s stipulate up front that the facility with devices thing is very real and very much worth paying attention to, for lots of reasons. That our then-three-year-old daughter could unlock and control an iPhone with greater ease than my parents could has broad implications for device manufacturers and those who write software for them. It is also an example of the accumulated baggage that learned habits and expectations can bring. Those are interesting, serious issues that deserve study. But that’s not the problem that bugs me.</p>
<p>This is: too many journalism students and journalists are native <em>users</em> rather than actual natives. The difference is enormous, and has real implications. Actual natives can build in addition to use digital tools, giving themselves many more opportunities to make better journalism. Users can only work within the constraints that other people set.</p>
<p>When I’m teaching classes or looking at resumes of journalism students, I see a lot of this kind of thing, usually on a hosted WordPress install:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Skills: WordPress, Microsoft Office, social media</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Those are useful skills, to a point, but if you’re coming out of journalism school and those are your big technical skills, congratulations: you’ve just joined nearly all of your peers in almost every discipline. You can use TweetDeck? Great. Did you hand-code at least part of your “professional vanity site”? Do you actually know how the Internet works? I’ve come across too many journalism students who believe (or have been led to believe) that they are technologically adept, only to find that when it comes to how things online actually work, their knowledge is broad but very shallow. For example, I routinely find that most of my students are unaware of search engines’ advanced search capabilities, let alone that computers have powerful command-line interfaces.</p>
<p>Most of my students are not what I would call digital natives. They are more like users, and while journalism needs users, it desperately needs creators. Otherwise we all end up using what other people make, and we end up making fewer great things for our readers.</p>
<p>When people see themselves as users, they grow nervous at tinkering with the building blocks. They actually shy away from learning, because learning can be so much harder than just using a finished something handed to you. It’s ok to be nervous about new concepts, but what I’ve seen increasingly from journalism students is an incuriosity that borders on indifference. Part of this is the sweet lull of search results, something we all fall prey to. You know about this: you search for something and if it’s not in the first page or two of results, you presume it’s either a) unknowable or b) too hard to get at. The end result is a feeling of powerlessness, like this from the <a href="http://www.poynter.org/latest-news/top-stories/223548/online-course-shows-impact-importance-of-data-driven-journalism/">Poynter piece</a>:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>What I hated about week four (sorry Jeremy, you’re still amazing) was how paralyzed I felt. These data journalists and news developers seemed so far ahead. How were the rest of us with limited coding skills going to grapple with foreign languages like Ruby on Rails?</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’ve talked to journalism instructors who have experienced this and it seems to be one of the most frustrating things out there. Maybe the worst moment I’ve had as a journalism teacher is when a <em>graduate</em> student asked me, in the middle of class: “How are we expected to learn if you don’t teach us?” My first thought, which I safely kept unspoken, was: “How did you make it this far?” Because I don’t think that sort of approach is likely to lead to a journalism career that is successful or enjoyable. I’m pretty sure that if journalism ever needed incurious people, it surely cannot survive with them now.</p>
<p>The best journalists (and students) I know force themselves into uncomfortable situations when it comes to learning. They are not content to be handed information and just accept it. They want to explore, to figure things out, even when there’s some risk of failure there. There are examples from the “digital native” generation, folks like <a href="http://www.greglinch.com/">Greg Linch</a>, who wasn’t content to use WordPress but dove into ways to extend it and fit it to journalism’s needs. Or <a href="http://michelleminkoff.com/">Michelle Minkoff</a> or <a href="http://heatherlynnbrady.com/">Heather Brady</a>, two former students of mine. I’ve never known any of them to say, “That looks hard and I don’t know anything about it, so I’ll just avoid it.” Paralysis ensures that you’ll stay where you are. The very worst that could happen if you choose to dive in is that you fail and, in failing, learn something.</p>
<p>Many journalism students might rightly point out that their curriculums didn’t exactly demand this kind of approach, and to the extent that’s the case, that’s not their fault. But it is still an excuse, in the sense that a flawed curriculum can’t literally stop you from learning. So what can you do? Try things. Some suggestions:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>If you use WordPress, try to write an extension. Or take a theme you like and build a flat HTML site of your own.</li>
<li>If you know how to use Excel, try learning a database like <a href="https://github.com/tthibo/SQL-Tutorial/blob/master/tutorial_files/part1.textile">SQLite</a> (it’s in your phone and the Firefox browser).</li>
<li>Open the Terminal on your Mac laptop. <a href="http://blog.teamtreehouse.com/introduction-to-the-mac-os-x-command-line">Learn some commands</a> in order to do things like connect to the web. You can do much of the same stuff on Windows, believe it or not.</li>
<li>Spend more time reading the source of web pages. Copy the parts you like or don’t understand, and study them.</li>
<li>Download <a href="https://blog.twitter.com/2012/your-twitter-archive">your Twitter archive</a> and analyze it in Excel or SQLite.</li>
<li>Learn how to connect to the <a href="https://apigee.com/console/twitter">Twitter</a> or <a href="https://apigee.com/console/facebook">Facebook</a> API and retrieve information from it, even in a web browser.</li>
<li>Pick a journalism problem you have (maybe a site you check often doesn’t have an RSS feed) and try to solve it.</li>
</ol>
<p>Notice that I didn’t say, “everyone must learn to code.” I don’t advocate learning to code for its own sake, or for everyone. Have a problem in mind, or a story you want to tell. If you need code to do that, then there’s your opening. For the sake of your own career, if not the state of the industry, what you should fear are points in the process of doing journalism where you have to say, “I don’t know how to do that” and hand your story - the story you care about - off to someone else with no understanding of what they are about to do. That fear should motivate you to learn, and learning is contagious. More importantly, you should <em>want</em> to learn, to be excited about learning. Be curious. Newsrooms are filled with restless people looking for great stories, wondering how to explain the world. How can someone be “digitally savvy” and yet filled with dread about exploring the digital world?</p>
<p>Building isn’t just more useful than being a user, it’s also more empowering. Of course there are times when building and creating is filled with frustration, but in most cases that frustration is your own. You have a better chance of resolving that feeling than if you sit around waiting for someone else to solve your problems for you. Journalism needs problem solvers and creators so that we can make users out of more people. Next time you encounter a new and unfamiliar technology or skill, take that nervous energy and use it to improve yourself. We’ll all be better off if you do.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2013/10/01/the-natives-arent-restless-enough/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2013 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Teaching Hospitals, Journalism Education and a Hatchet Job</title>
  <dc:creator>Derek Willis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2013/08/22/teaching-hospitals-journalism-education-and-a-hatchet-job/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><a href="https://twitter.com/donica">Donica Mensing</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/dryfe">David Ryfe</a> from the Reynolds School of Journalism at the University of Nevada, Reno, have published <a href="http://www.academia.edu/3412374/Blueprint_for_Change_From_the_Teaching_Hospital_to_the_Entrepreneurial_Model_of_Journalism_Education">a paper</a> that attempts to argue that recent attempts by foundations and others advocating for a “<a href="http://www.knightfoundation.org/press-room/other/open-letter-americas-university-presidents/">teaching hospital</a>” approach to journalism education, while well-intentioned, is actually some sort of “back to the future” plan that would enshrine the journalistic norms of the 1960s and (I am not making this up, I swear) “could actually slow the response to change” by journalism schools.</p>
<p>Three questions come to mind: First, could anything <em>really</em> slow the response we’ve seen so far from academia? Second, is that what the teaching hospital model is really about? And third, this is scholarship?</p>
<p>The paper is not purely a critique of the teaching hospital method, although it surely approaches that task with fervor. It also advocates for an “entrepreneurial model” of journalism education, saying that “the groundswell of grassroots activity in civic entrepreneurship, social innovation, user centered design and related practices represent a reservoir of potential energy that could invigorate journalism education.”</p>
<p>Ah, buzzword bingo, that hallmark of well-grounded research. Tell me, exactly, how “user centered design” and these other concepts cannot be taught through doing, only learned through the entrepreneurship process?</p>
<p>The easiest way to win an argument is to make the other side so unappealing that no rational person would choose it. This is done through a variety of methods: the use of straw men, unsupported claims and other tactics common to, say, Lee Atwater. An important part is to attribute things to your opponent that sound awful but possible. That’s what Mensing and Ryfe do in this paper.</p>
<p>In describing the teaching hospital model of journalism education, they write that it:</p>
<ul>
<li>“implies that journalism is a settled profession with clear boundaries that needs only to be practiced more rigorously, instead of a field with its most fundamental premises unraveling”</li>
<li>“makes it hard for students to think differently”</li>
<li>argues that “the core of journalism is sound and the problems faced by the news industry are primarily technological and economic”</li>
<li>“forecasts a future for journalism that is infused with the practices of the past”</li>
<li>assumes that the answers to the question of how to add value to democratic community are “fixed and eternal”</li>
<li>calls for “saving the journalism industry by turning journalism schools into production facilities staffed by industry professionals who have left an industry in deep distress”</li>
</ul>
<p>Just two of those claims has a cited reference (one is a paper by one of the authors). The reader is led to believe that, having surveyed the teaching hospital model, the authors have found that it is regressive, inflexible and hopelessly tied to the past.</p>
<p>That sounds pretty bad, right? Is there some real evidence for those assertions? Did the authors conduct a survey of journalism school practices and outcomes? Unearth a statement by the “teaching hospital advocates” that plants a flag in the soil of regressive education practices?</p>
<p>No, they didn’t. Here’s what Eric Newton, an author of the teaching hospital open letter linked above, <a href="http://www.niemanlab.org/2013/08/do-journalism-schools-really-need-to-be-teaching-hospitals/#comment-1010807645">had to say about the teaching hospital model</a>:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“Teaching Hospital” Model: A model of learning-by-doing that includes college students, professors and professionals working together under one ‘digital roof’ for the benefit of a community. Student journalists provide news and engage the community in innovative ways. Top professionals support and guide them. Good researchers help design and study their experiments.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>If it’s old school, it’s not a teaching hospital. If it doesn’t include research, it’s not a teaching hospital. If it doesn’t engage the community, it’s not a teaching hospital. If professors and professionals don’t set aside their long-standing arguments and work together, it’s not a teaching hospital.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Teaching hospitals help invent and test new things. That’s why a group of funders said at this year’s journalism education convention that we are working on a micro-granting competition. The grant program, to be announced later this year, will support “live news experiments.” We hope that good examples will clarify what good journalistic teaching hospitals should do.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>At this point, I should say that <a href="http://blog.openelections.net">a project that I co-founded</a> is a recipient of money from the Knight Foundation, where Eric works. I’ve never met Eric, nor have we communicated on the subject of journalism education.</p>
<p>If you read that definition (and the <a href="http://www.knightfoundation.org/press-room/other/open-letter-americas-university-presidents/">open letter</a>) it might strike you as not at all what Mensing and Ryfe describe. Yet somehow they’ve cast it in this rather negative light. As <a href="https://twitter.com/Brizzyc">Carrie Brown-Smith</a>, a professor at the University of Memphis, put it: “<a href="http://www.niemanlab.org/2013/08/do-journalism-schools-really-need-to-be-teaching-hospitals/#comment-1011505711">I’m just unclear who or what is actually being rebutted here</a>.” You and me both, Doctor.</p>
<p>There are no reasons why teaching hospital models cannot be “entrepreneurial” in the manner described by the authors. Indeed, there are <a href="http://www.ist.rit.edu/~jxs/classes/proposed/JournPubIn21stCent.html">examples</a> of <a href="http://homicidewatch.org/2013/08/20/what-weve-learned-homicide-watch-dcs-student-reporting-lab/">this</a> that combine the best ideas of both models. I am not aware of anyone advocating for a regressive teaching hospital model the authors describe. If they are, they do not cite any in the paper (and if they know of some, why wouldn’t they cite it?).</p>
<p>To the extent that journalism schools are failing to keep pace with the very real changes in the practice of journalism (professional or not), it’s very hard to see how the involving more professionals in the process is a harmful thing. But that’s not what the authors argue against - they write that teaching hospital advocates are seeking to <em>replace</em> existing faculty members with professionals “who have left an industry in deep distress”.</p>
<p>Let’s be very clear about this: there certainly are people who have left the industry to teach who are not well-suited to prepare students for doing journalism today. But if anything, a program in which such people actually worked alongside students and other faculty members in producing modern journalism would give them an opportunity to refit their skills and mindsets. The authors suggest that an entrepreneurial approach would attract non-journalism instructors to the process, but it’s not clear that <em>current</em> faculty would accept this or that such outside experts really want to teach journalism.</p>
<p>In a comment discussing the paper on Nieman Lab, <a href="http://www.niemanlab.org/2013/08/do-journalism-schools-really-need-to-be-teaching-hospitals/#comment-1011552411">Mensing writes</a> that “In the end, it’s not an either/or argument. It’s an AND argument – we need teaching hospitals AND other educational models.” But that’s not at all what the paper says. The paper characterizes the teaching hospital model as a relic from the past with a few redeeming values (“a handful of well-funded schools may benefit,” they concede), but the system they describe is not the same one that its proponents have outlined.</p>
<p>I learned journalism by doing, with some useful assistance in the classroom. Almost all of my important lessons about journalism came while practicing it, and almost all of my creative learning happened that way, too. There is nothing wrong with injecting some entrepreneurial life into the teaching and doing of journalism. There is something very wrong with claiming that the teaching hospital model would be harmful for students without actually verifying that claim.</p>
<p>This paper sets up the teaching hospital model as a straw man standing in the way of a more flexible, creative and successful model of journalism education, and proceeds to cut that straw man down in order to make the other model look better. The authors write that they wish to “build on this conversation” surrounding the future of journalism education, but instead the reader is treated to a lesson in how to win an argument by stacking the deck.</p>
<p>Mensing, to her credit, seems to pull back a bit from the aggressive critique of the paper in <a href="http://www.niemanlab.org/2013/08/do-journalism-schools-really-need-to-be-teaching-hospitals/#comment-1011552411">her comment on Nieman Lab</a>, writing that “I guess the next logical step is to stop arguing and actually study what j-schools are doing so we learn what really is most effective for teaching.” Wait, you and Ryfe wrote the paper <em>before</em> studying what j-schools are actually doing? That’s not scholarship; it reads more like a hatchet job.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2013/08/22/teaching-hospitals-journalism-education-and-a-hatchet-job/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2013 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Why Develop in the Newsroom?</title>
  <dc:creator>Derek Willis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2013/07/16/why-develop-in-the-newsroom/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Nearly a decade ago, I sat with a group of Python developers around a table at a Vietnamese restaurant in Washington, D.C.’s Cleveland Park neighborhood and told them what it was like to work at a newspaper.</p>
<p>Every day, I said, we go out and collect as much information as we can about possible stories, but only some of that information actually turns into stories and only some of those stories get published. Then we wake up the next day and do it again, largely from scratch!</p>
<p>They were horrified.</p>
<p>News organizations are inefficient, often <a href="http://thescoop.org/thefix/the-information-gap/">far too cavalier</a> about the raw materials that provide their lifeblood and can seem to lurch from story to story without a whole lot of reason. Many journalists have a bizarre fear of math and computers, and guaranteed a secret ballot, a decent portion might opt for a return to the days of typewriters and afternoon editions.</p>
<p>But all of this hides a beautiful opportunity, an underbelly filled with ever-changing stories and challenges, and a chance to make an impact beyond the web. For some developers, especially those who are engaged with the world beyond Github, newsrooms are quite a natural fit, even if you’ve never thought about it.</p>
<p>Why? Because we are storytellers. When you’ve solved some tricky bug in your code, what do you really want to do? Tell someone about it. So you blog, tweet or even walk over to someone else and begin the story: “You won’t believe this thing I just had to deal with!”</p>
<p>We’re seekers. You find something on the web that’s amazing or tragic or wonderful or confounding, and you want to share it: “Hey, you have got to see this.” And then you want to find something else.</p>
<p>Newsrooms also attract misfits, in the best possible sense of the word. You’ll find people willing to ask questions until they find answers, who want to understand things and try to pry the facts out of sources, whether those sources are other people, documents or data. Finding interesting things and telling people about them is at the very heart of what we do.</p>
<p>Here’s where you come in, though: we have too many things to look at, too many places to find information and a variety of audiences to satisfy. We need the help, whether that’s in <a href="http://thescoop.org/thefix/better-tools/">making it easier for reporters to find the news</a> in reams of text or providing a way to <a href="http://brianabelson.com/open-news/2013/03/18/A-Metric-For-News-Apps.html">track what keeps readers coming back</a>. We do quite a bit of our work in the open, as you’ll discover once your name is in a byline. Our users react.</p>
<p>If you’re interested in social applications, consider that newsrooms have been collecting <a href="http://tdn.com/lifestyles/announcements/births/">birth</a>, <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/pages/fashion/weddings/index.html">wedding</a> and <a href="http://www.detroitnews.com/section/OBITUARIES">death announcements</a> for years. They have been piling up information about crime, schools, elections and sports team for decades. Sure, a lot of it that data will be unstructured, or worse. But imagine being able to tell <a href="http://projects.latimes.com/hollywood/star-walk/">the story of a landmark</a> in a new way, or being able to create the app that <a href="http://projects.latimes.com/lakers/">settles all arguments about your favorite sports team</a>.</p>
<p>And if you’re interested in contributing to our shared civic life, where we learn about the issues that define us and our future, there are few better places to be. We are not campaigners in the usual sense, but our mission is a better-informed and active citizenry, and newsrooms have a built-in platform for driving that effort. We do things that are not popular in the conventional sense but are <a href="http://projects.nytimes.com/guantanamo">necessary for a free society</a> or <a href="http://projects.nytimes.com/toxic-waters">shed light on an important issue</a>. Newsrooms are about <a href="http://apps.beta620.nytimes.com/timesmachine/1914/06/29/issue.html">war</a> and peace, <a href="http://apps.npr.org/arrested-development/">laughter</a> and <a href="http://crime.chicagotribune.com/chicago/homicides">pain</a> and every aspect of our world.</p>
<p>Look, newsrooms have issues to spare. I won’t pretend that many of them aren’t prone to hesitation and at times resistant to new ideas. They have loads of debt, of the monetary, legacy and technical varieties. Our audience is being replaced while we publish, with few guarantees that today’s readers and listeners will be there tomorrow. But newsrooms are also a gateway to a wider world and a broader understanding of who we all are together.</p>
<p>If you have solid web development skills, chances are you’re not hurting for employment opportunities. There are plenty of organizations, large and small, established and new, that want to build things for the web, tablets, phones and more. So why come develop in a newsroom? Sure, we need you. But you can be a witness to and a participant in extraordinary events.</p>
<p>Interested? Check out the <a href="http://www.mozillaopennews.org/fellowships/">Knight-Mozilla fellowships</a>, which place talented developers in newsrooms that want and need your help, and consider applying.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2013/07/16/why-develop-in-the-newsroom/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jul 2013 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>What Good is Dat?</title>
  <dc:creator>Derek Willis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2013/07/02/what-good-is-dat/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Max Ogden, a <a href="https://github.com/maxogden?tab=repositories">one-man band</a> of interesting civic (and other) coding, has a new project called <a href="https://github.com/maxogden/dat"><code>dat</code></a>. <code>Dat</code> is “a new initiative that seeks to increase the traction of the open data movement by providing better tools for collaboration.” In practical terms, <code>dat</code> will consist of a set of tools to “store, synchronize, manipulate and collaborate in a decentralized fashion on sets of data, hopefully enabling platforms analogous to GitHub to be built on top of it.”</p>
<p>Great! More data tools! Or: Great. More data tools.</p>
<p>Github’s Ben Balter falls into the latter camp, asking <a href="http://ben.balter.com/2013/07/01/technologys-the-easy-part/">why more tools for government data are needed</a>: “It’s the culture that we’ve go to worry about. Will the solution be adopted by the agency? Will existing habits subvert the cool thing you just made? Will the dream live on once you’re at your next gig? If you ignore culture, even the most elegant of technological solutions can be relegated to a dusty shelf as nothing more than the right solution to the wrong problem.”</p>
<p>Ben has worked inside government and outside it. He’s not uninformed when it comes to this stuff. And he has a fairly accurate assessment of the whole government data scene:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I watch day in and day out as many of my former colleagues fight tooth-and-nail trying to convince well-meaning government bureaucrats to toss a scrap of government data over the firewall. It’s a tiring process. After all, whack-a-mole is, by definition, a loosing (sic) game. But the answer’s not Yet Another Mallet, nor is it to give up and build our own mole management solution. We should be making it dumb-simple to do the right thing. We should be building really, really boring stuff. The more boring the better. In many cases, we probably shouldn’t be building anything at all. This is one of them.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Max provides <a href="https://github.com/maxogden/dat#why-not-just-use-git">a response</a> that addresses why <code>git</code> and Github don’t fit the bill for this project, but his response isn’t particularly relevant to my interests anyway. Ben’s right: the technology isn’t the issue. But that’s why I think <code>dat</code> is a good thing: because the best part of it, the thing that makes it exciting to me, is boring but essential and not really about the technology. It’s not the tools to store or synchronize the data. It’s not even the bit about transforming it into more useful formats.</p>
<p>It is the simple idea that if enough people use <code>dat</code> to explore government data, they will find the best and worst of it, document it and ultimately produce better things. This has been the case in my experience with campaign finance data, which requires solutions for storage, synchronization and transformation. Those of us who work with it have our own approaches, but the best things happen when we collaborate on our methodologies. We reduce the chance that any of us display or report figures that conflict with each other, and crucially, we learn more about the data in doing so.</p>
<p>That’s what I’m looking forward to in <code>dat</code> - a true platform for collaboration that enables users of government data to annotate it and to share their experiences in the hopes of creating a set of best practices for individual datasets. Maybe that won’t happen, or maybe the technical aspects will prove more popular than the collaborative ones. But the more opportunities for collaboration, the better, and I’m glad to see another one underway.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2013/07/02/what-good-is-dat/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2013 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Lessons from ‘Data-Crunched Democracy’</title>
  <dc:creator>Derek Willis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2013/06/04/lessons-from-data-crunched-democracy/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Last Friday I traveled to Philadelphia for <a href="http://datapolitics.jomc.unc.edu/about/">Data-Crunched Democracy</a>, a conference drawing together political consultants, data analysis and targeting professionals, academics and journalists to discuss the impacts of “big data” on elections. This cross-disciplinary approach made for some very interesting discussions and I met a number of fascinating people (including, as it happened, the prodigious <a href="http://xenocrypt.blogspot.com/">Xenocrypt</a>). Rasmus Kleis Nielsen has a <a href="http://rasmuskleisnielsen.net/2013/05/31/data-crunched-democracy/">good overview of the day</a>, but I wanted to write a bit about the lessons for journalists covering campaigns that engage in the use of data for targeting and predictive analysis.</p>
<section id="the-limits-of-obama-vs.-romney" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-limits-of-obama-vs.-romney">The Limits of Obama vs.&nbsp;Romney</h4>
<p>Many of the moderator and audience questions at the conference were focused on last year’s presidential campaign, and with good reason, but journalists need to absorb the important lessons and move on. Here is a quick list of <em>relatively unimportant questions</em> about data use from that campaign:</p>
<ul>
<li>How many people worked on the data team?</li>
<li>What percentage of the campaign budget was devoted to targeting? (If you want to be a wiseass, the correct answer is: as close to 100% as possible, depending on the definition of “targeting”)</li>
<li>Which commercial datasets were the most useful to the campaign?</li>
<li>Did you really track whether visitors to the campaign sites also visited pornography sites? (this still annoys the Romney folks)</li>
<li>How often did you pull my Facebook graph and Twitter feed?</li>
<li>How much data did you have?</li>
</ul>
<p>I wished that the organizers of the conference - who did a very good job - had blocked out 30 minutes at the start for an “Ask Me Anything About the 2012 Campaign” session, and then prohibited 2012-specific questions for the rest of the day, in order to draw the discussion towards the implications of such use and the lessons for all of us. There were times when we had that discussion, but there were other times when it kept circling back to some version of “How great, in your opinion, was the Obama campaign’s data use” or “Why didn’t the Romney campaign do X?”. As Ethan Roeder, an Obama campaign data staffer, put it on Twitter: “<a href="https://twitter.com/HardlyIfAtAll/status/340527402423840768">Obama campaign wasn’t all that and a bag of chips, bro.</a>”</p>
<p>The first thing we can do as journalists is to focus on the broader lessons and questions of the campaign, not rehash it.</p>
</section>
<section id="not-exactly-like-selling-orange-juice" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="not-exactly-like-selling-orange-juice">Not Exactly Like Selling Orange Juice</h4>
<p>Yes, there was some excellent journalism done about the campaigns’ use of data, particularly from <a href="http://www.thevictorylab.com/">Sasha Issenberg</a>, <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2012/11/when-the-nerds-go-marching-in/265325/">Alexis Madrigal</a> and <a href="http://www.propublica.org/article/everything-we-know-so-far-about-obamas-big-data-operation">Lois Beckett of ProPublica</a>. And it’s logical that much of the focus from the media and academics in this area has been on the 2012 presidential race; it featured two campaigns with massive resources and plans to engage and target voters in sophisticated ways. There are some really innovative techniques that we learned about, including <a href="http://gawker.com/5961202/how-the-obama-campaigns-data+miners-knew-what-you-were-watching-on-tv">the use of data recorded by television set-top boxes</a>. But even that Gawker piece seems to me to focus on the utility of such a tactic in the wrong way. As Carol Davidsen, who described the process at the conference, said, “behavior data is more interesting than consumer data,” and the campaign was looking to spend its television ad budget wisely. So running ads on a specific cable network during a specific time period becomes less about targeting specific individuals - Davidsen pointed out that while TV viewership hasn’t slacked off, people are doing other things <em>while</em> the TV is on - and more about getting a better value for the campaign’s ad budget. Yes, it’s targeting. But what I heard from the people who do campaign targeting is that a lot of what’s possible is fuzzy at best. It’s very hard to get down to targeting individuals precisely using data from social media or other sources beyond a voter file.</p>
<p>There are too many occasions when the press has conflated political data work with the most common use case: <a href="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424127887323353204578126671124151266.html">selling stuff to consumers</a>. Elections are not like selling orange juice; rather, they are like selling orange juice to people who drink it infrequently, are often ambivalent about it and can change their minds based on what may seem tangential issues. In other words, it’s hard, and that difficulty matters both to the process and how journalists explain it. Political campaigns have not and cannot just take corporate data mining practices and plug them into a political campaign; it’s a different process, one that actually has <em>less</em> data.</p>
<p>Listen to Alex Lundry of TargetPoint Consulting, who worked on the Romney campaign: “What we’re doing is building data bridges, but to data islands. There are no individuals, only aggregates. There are bridges, but our ability to work on those islands is limited.” Some of the academics accused the targeting folks of playing down the effectiveness of their techniques, as if they were saying that this stuff doesn’t work. I don’t believe that’s the point they were making. The point, which journalists in particular need to understand, is that integrating data sets is a messy, unreliable and hard business. I usually tell students of mine that at least 75 percent of the time they spend with data is doing stuff <em>before</em> the analysis: acquiring, cleaning, standardizing, figuring out the limits of it. Lundry put that number at north of 90 percent at the conference. So there are no magic bullets here, and the really valuable part is the voter file, not the other data. It would be convenient for journalists if the story of data use in the 2012 campaign turned on a single tactic or dataset, but it’s not true. We need to be honest with ourselves and our readers about what campaigns are trying, but especially what works, even if it’s not thrilling.</p>
</section>
<section id="keep-calm-and-write-sensibly" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="keep-calm-and-write-sensibly">Keep Calm and Write Sensibly</h4>
<p>There was some pushback from campaign staff towards the media for its reporting on data and privacy, that we’ve gotten alarmist and are scaring readers. I think they have a point, in that the world we describe too often sounds like, as one panelist put it, “a Tom Clancy novel” where everyone assumes that they are being followed all the time. I’m not saying there is no danger of abuse or misuse of personal data - a campaign staffer could disclose personal information about voters in a number of ways - but I do think the journalists need to recognize that most campaigns are built on a simple model: do what’s necessary to win. That often means that big plans that you and I might dream up for massive digital surveillance don’t happen because campaigns don’t have the time, staff or incentive to conduct them. It doesn’t mean that campaigns are always good actors, however, and journalists need to be able to understand the technology enough to tell the difference.</p>
<p>During the presidential campaign, the Times (and I presume other outlets) was pitched a story by one side about the Internet practices of the other, with the implication being that the other side wasn’t playing by rules barring coordination among separate committees. While it was technically possible that such skullduggery was afoot, there was no proof (or even very solid evidence). I imagine it would be tough for many reporters to be able to judge the situation, considering that it turned on how Web analytics were being used and identified. Ultimately, we did not publish a story, and when I asked one of the original sources of the pitch about it after the election, this person laughed in a fairly sheepish way. They tried: it was a campaign, after all. You want to win.</p>
<p>So yes, the media has its problems in accurately writing about data use, privacy and the Web components of modern political campaigns, but let’s not forget that the campaigns have an interest in painting each other as bad actors, too, and journalism has a role in trying to figure out such claims. Which means that journalists need to understand how sites track visitors. Your own analytics department would be a good place to start. And then we need to write calmly about the tactics and implications. This approach, perhaps best exemplified by <a href="http://www.propublica.org/article/message-machine-starts-providing-answers">ProPublica’s Message Machine work</a>, tries to pull apart the campaign’s techniques without making them sound like they are some science-fiction tale. Campaign emails are a great place to start, because lots of people receive email, and it’s so cheap to send that there’s no incentive for the campaigns not to experiment. When that approach becomes possible with television advertising (an area Lundry calls “ripe for innovation”), we need to be ready for it, as difficult as it may be to track.</p>
</section>
<section id="focus-on-the-basics" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="focus-on-the-basics">Focus on the Basics</h4>
<p>Because a lot of this data stuff seems like rocket science to most journalists, there’s the temptation to believe that data science can do anything, and that anything is possible. But when it comes to campaign data, it all starts and ends with the voter files - registration and voter history information. That’s the core data asset, and everything else is built atop it. You can’t really start with, say, a file detailing magazine subscriptions and build an effective campaign. Lundry called the information gathered by volunteers or paid canvassers “solid gold” to a campaign, because it is collected by a person who is able to talk to potential voters.</p>
<p>From that point, the workings can get a little obscure, as campaigns try to integrate data from the voter files with information they have collected. Part of that is the commercial data, but only part, and its predictive value doesn’t always rival that of voter history files and partisan leanings (particularly in the past few elections). For journalists, the lesson is clear: we should at least have what campaigns start with in terms of voter data: voter registration, voter history and political geographies. In many states, these are freely available (although, as <a href="https://twitter.com/kwcollins/status/340522066883256321">Kevin Collins notes</a>, that’s not universally true). The campaigns were updating their voter data monthly, then weekly, then daily as the election neared. Are we doing anything similar?</p>
<p>I hear the cry: “But what about social media?” Here’s what Rayid Ghani, the Obama campaign’s chief data scientist, said at the conference: “So far there hasn’t been a good way to connect that with the voter file.” The piles of Facebook Likes, the retweets and reblogged Tumblr posts - they are all interesting things, but how relevant are they if a sizable chunk of your social audience either lives outside the United States or isn’t eligible to vote for some other reason (age, for example)? The most interesting question from the 2012 election, to me, is how the Obama campaign managed to <em>find</em> additional voters and turn them out. Some of that is due to predictive modeling. But some of it is likely due to really diligent in-person field work. We should strive to understand all the parts of the effort.</p>
<p>One way to do that is to follow the people who did targeting work as they now go on to other things. Many are still involved in politics at the national level, including folks like Lundry. Others, like Obama’s former Wisconsin field operations lead Hallie Montoya Tansey, are looking down the ballot. She and a friend have founded The Target Labs <a href="http://halliemt.tumblr.com/post/52067134663/my-new-adventure-the-target-labs">to provide prediction services to campaigns</a>. Why? Here’s what she says about working for Obama in Wisconsin:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“The reason we were reaching out to voters outside of the Democratic strongholds in Madison and Milwaukee is because we were using data analytics to build models that used all the information we had about voters, including demographics, geography, and past voting history, to make extremely accurate predictions about how likely they were to support us. These models made it possible to find ‘our voters’ on every block in every region of the state. In 2004, John Kerry won Wisconsin by 10,000 votes. In 2008, our margin of victory was 400,000. Although I’d worked on many campaigns before, this was my first experience using predictive modeling, and it convinced me completely of the potential of these techniques, adopted at scale, to change the way campaigns are run.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>News organizations should be doing post-mortems using 2004, 2008 and 2012 voter history and registration data to figure out where the “new” voters came from, who they might be and how solid they are in terms of voting behavior. Although no one at the conference was certain that micro-targeting would become a staple of every campaign anytime soon, I think we all acknowledged that it is coming to an election near you. That warning applies to journalists, too. The way to start is to begin valuing information about voters as much as campaigns do, and to try and emulate the data efforts of the campaigns, so that we can more accurately assess their work.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2013/06/04/lessons-from-data-crunched-democracy/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2013 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>What They Say About Us</title>
  <dc:creator>Derek Willis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2013/05/21/what-they-say-about-us/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>As journalism buzzwords go these days, analytics has a lot going for it. The term is broad enough to encompass a wide range of ideas, ranging from the “<a href="http://sloanreview.mit.edu/article/ken-auletta-on-the-dark-side-of-applying-analytics-to-journalism/">dark side</a>” where the application of analytics leads to bad and banal writing to the use of analytics by reporters <a href="http://lauraamico.tumblr.com/post/5196806316/reporting-from-analytics-example">to unearth details of breaking news</a>. Knowing who views our work and how they interact with it, while not a savior of the industry, seems like something we should be paying attention to and incorporating into newsroom processes.</p>
<p>But I’m also interested in another form of analytics: how other people cite, describe and otherwise use the information we publish. Yes, the number of Facebook likes or Twitter retweets that a story gets can tell you something about how popular it is. But what about the people who take the time to describe a story on social media in their own words, or pick their favorite quote? Aren’t they arguably more invested in it, <a href="https://twitter.com/Jo_1972/status/336415782344994816">maybe even personally involved</a>?</p>
<p>A few weeks ago, my colleagues in Interactive News at The Times held a hack day focusing on analytics, and built some really interesting and useful stuff that will help improve our internal knowledge of our own applications and how users are interacting with them. <a href="http://tweetrewrite.herokuapp.com/">My own contribution</a> was much less technically impressive, and we’ll get to that in a bit. But it scratched an itch that had started several years ago when I saw <a href="http://linkypedia.inkdroid.org/">linkypedia</a>, a site built by my friend <a href="http://inkdroid.org/journal/about/">Ed Summers</a>. Ed works at the Library of Congress, which means he cares a lot about not just preserving information but also making it easy to reference. He also, via his work on a <a href="http://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/">historic newspaper preservation project called Chronicling America</a>, knows a bit about the news industry.</p>
<p>The idea behind linkypedia is that links on Wikipedia aren’t just references, they help describe how digital collections are used on the Web, and <a href="http://linkypedia.inkdroid.org/about/">encourage the spread of knowledge</a>: “if organizations can see how their web content is being used in Wikipedia, they will be encouraged and emboldened to do more.” When I first saw it, I immediately thought about how New York Times content was being cited on Wikipedia. Because it’s an <a href="https://github.com/edsu/linkypedia">open source project</a>, I was able to find out, and it turned out (at least back then) that many Civil War-era stories that had been digitized were linked to from the site. I had no idea, and wondered how many of my colleagues knew. Then I wondered what else we didn’t know about how our content is being used outside the friendly confines of nytimes.com.</p>
<p>That’s the thread that leads from Linkypedia to <a href="http://tweetrewrite.herokuapp.com/">TweetRewrite</a>, my “analytics” hack that takes a nytimes.com URL and finds tweets that aren’t simply automatic retweets; it tries to filter out posts that contain the exact headline of the story to find <a href="http://tweetrewrite.herokuapp.com/show?url=http://www.nytimes.com/2013/05/21/business/apple-avoided-billions-in-taxes-congressional-panel-says.html?hp&amp;_r=0">what people say about it</a>. It’s a <a href="https://github.com/dwillis/times_dialect">pretty simple Ruby app</a> that uses Sinatra, the Twitter and Bitly gems and a <a href="https://github.com/nytimes/times_wire">library</a> I wrote to pull details about a story from the Times Newswire API.</p>
<p>Seems to me that the more we know about how our content is cited, the more we might be able to find out about our users or how they value the journalism we produce. Maybe there are product ideas in that knowledge: if people are relying on our stories for certain purposes, it’s possible that we could create custom packages and charge for them. At the very least, such insights on social media might give us an idea of how people spread stories, and maybe we can learn from that. Tracing links are just a start; we could do the same for entire passages, appearances by New York Times staff in other media and more. <a href="http://dwillis.github.io/paper-of-record/?apikey=474754a0d230cc71b31b8bf6d313b70c&amp;notify=false">Another project of mine</a> uses the <a href="http://sunlightlabs.github.io/Capitol-Words/">Capitol Words API</a> from the Sunlight Foundation to track mentions of The Times in the Congressional Record. If we’re lucky, people talk and write about us a lot. We should be listening and watching for what they say.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2013/05/21/what-they-say-about-us/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 21 May 2013 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Academy Fight Song</title>
  <dc:creator>Derek Willis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2013/04/28/academy-fight-song/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><em>What’s that I hear</em><br>
<em>The sound of marching feet</em><br>
<em>It has a strange allure</em><br>
<em>Has a strange allure</em><br>
Mission of Burma, “Academy Fight Song”</p>
<p><em>Disclaimer: I am the son and son-in-law of retired tenured university professors, and have taught data reporting skills for about 10 years at the undergraduate and graduate levels. I love teaching. I have my issues with “education”.</em></p>
<p><a href="http://mindymcadams.com/tojou/2013/journalism-curriculum-and-the-hands-in-the-air-approach/">This post on journalism curriculum</a> by University of Florida journalism professor Mindy McAdams deserves to be widely read. Not just because it attempts to deal with a growing problem in a responsible manner, but because it is honest about the situation:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Students deserve better. Regardless of what they think journalism is when they tick the box to become a journalism major (and regardless of whether they’re paying Ivy League prices or in-state tuition at a public university), they deserve to be taught skills, techniques, and ways of thinking that will carry them through the challenging times at hand and ahead. They deserve to have every teacher — tenured, adjunct or freshly pressed Ph.D.&nbsp;— looking at what’s new, what’s happening today, now (what happened in and around Boston last week, for example, as seen in the mainstream news and in social media) and incorporating new methods for reporting, for storytelling, and for engaging the audience into all of their classes.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Mindy has been teaching her students this semester about coding for journalism, and has a blog where she has described her experiences and posted her <a href="http://mindymcadams.com/tojou/2013/code-for-journalism-students-presentations/">presentations</a>. Here’s a wacky question: why isn’t this stuff (blog posts, presentations, videos) on a ufl.edu site? Maybe it makes no difference at all to students, but why wouldn’t the UF Journalism school want to be all over this stuff?</p>
<p>Mindy’s post is a response to <a href="http://www.poynter.org/latest-news/the-next-journalism/210196/why-we-need-a-better-conversation-about-the-future-of-journalism-education/">an earlier one on Poynter</a> by Tom Rosenstiel in which he argues that journalism education was, in fact, experimenting in the kinds of ways that are needed for the future of the profession. He cites, among others, <a href="http://www.niemanlab.org/2012/09/robert-hernandez-reboot-journalism-school-take-control-of-your-education-instead/">Robert Hernandez</a> at USC and <a href="http://journalism.missouri.edu/staff/esther-thorson/">Esther Thorson</a> at Missouri as doing important work in the frontiers of journalism.</p>
<p>Fair enough, although I’d argue that rather than “barely scratching the surface”, Rosenstiel probably couldn’t generate a list of people doing innovative work in academia that was all that much longer than what he published. Katie Zhu, who is pursuing a double major in computer science and journalism at Northwestern, writes that she has had one professor – at <em>Medill</em> – who she can honestly describe as a person who “<a href="https://medium.com/i-m-h-o/b8d43e4c204d">get[s] it</a>.” Think about that. Here we have a bright, talented and ambitious student who wants to put herself at the forefront of journalism education and has to do it by herself at one of the elite journalism schools in the country. As Katie says:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Let’s re-architect the distribution requirements so we can get rid of this notion that journalism and engineering (and the sciences) are at odds with each other. Because journalism needs to move forward.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The unspoken part there is that, if this keeps happening to enough people (and there will be more), journalism will move forward <a href="http://forjournalism.com/">without journalism education</a>, or worse, talented would-be journalists will seek to work in other professions. Katie has a job lined up at Twitter.</p>
<section id="anti-intellectualisms-roots" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="anti-intellectualisms-roots">Anti-Intellectualism’s Roots</h3>
<p>Part of the problem is that some of these technical areas and concepts are alien to many faculty, and part of it is that it’s sometimes hard to attract experts from the profession to full-time academic work. Part of it is that curriculum change is insanely harder than it should be, and that accreditation is so super important – to other academics, at least. Part of it is the tenure system, which results in disproportionate power within departments, power worth fighting to protect. And part of it is also that the academy has done a pretty terrible job of selling whatever <em>academic</em> products it creates, as well as pulling from the best the rest of the university has to offer.</p>
<p>For this, some blame (but only some) can be apportioned to the audience. As Rosenstiel writes:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>For years, journalism was marred by an ugly streak of anti-intellectualism — the denial of theory, the exaltation of craft, the repudiation [sic] professional identity, ignorance of scholarship. One byproduct of the crisis in journalism is that anti-intellectualism is giving way to something better at schools where practitioners and scholars work together to create a new curriculum.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>A fair point, but it goes a bit too far for me. For one thing, this anti-intellectualism that Rosenstiel identifies - surely that hasn’t been helped along by educators who tolerated and even encouraged the fiction that journalists “don’t need to know math” to do their work? As prevalent as that sentiment is in newsrooms, would it have become such a staple of journalism if there had been broad pushback from journalism schools? It’s fairly telling that <a href="https://math.temple.edu/~paulos/">John Allen Paulos’ website</a> is on the math.temple.edu server, because it sure as hell wouldn’t be found on a journalism school’s site (<em>to be clear: this isn’t a shot at Temple specifically, but at the academy generally. Temple has actually even <a href="http://sites.temple.edu/andrewmendelson/2011/09/temple-journalism-%E2%80%93-a-trajectory-of-curricular-innovation/">changed its curriculum</a>.</em>). The very fact that journalism schools have been looking outside their walls to address the industry’s current problems says an awful lot about how pervasive this anti-intellectualism really is, and what its sources really are.</p>
<p>Want more evidence? Let’s talk about this professor of practice thing. Or maybe these “general manager”-type positions in collegiate newsrooms (I have at least two friends, both former journalists, who are in these types of positions at prominent journalism schools). People: these are teachers, just as surely as any PhD on the faculty. Yes, it might be easier from a bureaucratic standpoint to get a “professor of practice” into the department, but I’m willing to bet a decent chunk of change that in the eyes of too many “real” professors, these people are not in a similar line of work or are doing it the wrong way. The people who have tried hard to get new ideas into the J-school are (mostly) dedicated and good people who see what is on the horizon. The people who resist are (mostly) dedicated and good people who have too much power and independence to give it up without a fight. This would be one hell of a good story, if only most journalism students were permitted to write about it.</p>
<p>A case in point: a few years ago I was invited to come to Northwestern for a week to speak to Medill faculty and students about the kinds of work we were doing, and to hold training sessions on basic data reporting concepts for the faculty. That I was there at all was hugely encouraging to me, and I met a number of faculty who, although inexperienced in this area, were excited about learning. And then I learned the catch: the training sessions were optional, because why would it be otherwise?. I struggle even now to imagine any journalism course in which the professor should remain ignorant of basic digital reporting knowledge. Great message for the faculty, let alone the students.</p>
</section>
<section id="its-academic" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="its-academic">It’s Academic</h3>
<p>The professional ignorance of scholarship thing, though, is certainly right from the perspective of someone who has worked in newsrooms since 1995 and has taught college classes for most of the past 10 years. I don’t read many academic journals, nor do I attend <a href="http://www.aejmc.org/">AEJMC</a> - go ahead, Google it - or other journalism education conferences, and I don’t know many professionals who do. Far worse is the fact that I would find it hard to read those papers anyway, since most of them are unavailable online without a subscription of some kind. Sure, we’ve been ignorant of scholarship. But I’m not sure that scholars have done what is truly necessary to improve the relationship between trade and education.</p>
<p>About a year ago I was involved in a brief Twitter episode <a href="http://thescoop.org/archives/2012/05/13/lost-in-the-weeds/">involving a draft academic paper that mentioned Fech</a>. Whatever my issues with the paper itself, there is a crazier undercurrent: one of its authors <a href="https://twitter.com/nikkiusher/status/201721394898280449">didn’t know that it was posted on the Web</a>, and as I learned, there was little chance that anyone outside academic circles would ever <em>see</em> the final paper. The authors very kindly sent me a revised version, but of course I can’t share that with you, and neither can they, legally. Which <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=J1sYN0PuRs4">makes no sense at all</a>. Academic authors are literally only publishing for themselves and their colleagues, and we can’t understand why the industry is so separated from the academy?</p>
<p>Of course the Internet is trying to undercut this closed system. There’s <a href="http://academia.edu/">academia.edu</a>, which as near as I can figure is like a Napster for journal (and other) articles, and it looks to me as if professors post their articles there even if they technically don’t have permission to do so. It would be funny if it weren’t sad, or if the news business wasn’t facing some pretty severe challenges. The kind of challenges that universities might be able to shed some light on through <a href="http://streamer.ist.rit.edu/~journo/classes/">smartly designed experiments</a> and <a href="http://www.niemanlab.org/tag/ethnographic-research/">research</a>. I’d be interested in reading more about those kinds of things directly rather than looking at <a href="http://cindyroyal.com/research.html">pages like this</a> and wishing there were more links.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-hard-part" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-hard-part">The Hard Part</h3>
<p>The gap between journalism and journalism education seems pretty big, although I think it’s hard to measure. Chalk at least some of that up to the peculiarities of both the profession and of academics in general, but there’s one factor that looms large: most other fields of study are not facing such a fundamental upheaval. It seems like this would be a pretty good time for there to be tighter collaboration between the industry and those who study it, or at least a reshaping of what those studies look like. But where to start?</p>
<p>Changing accreditation and tenure practices would be dramatic, but it’s hard to imagine either being done, both within journalism schools and across the academy more broadly. Even though I’ve never heard any journalism school graduate say that accreditation was any factor whatsoever in her decision to enroll, who wants to remove their name from <a href="http://www2.ku.edu/~acejmc/STUDENT/PROGLIST.SHTML">the list</a>? If one university (or department) changes its tenure practices, surely its competitors would use that against it when recruiting faculty.</p>
<p>Some prominent journalism grant-making organizations <a href="http://www.knightfoundation.org/press-room/other/open-letter-americas-university-presidents/">have urged the adoption of the teaching hospital method</a>, which makes some sense, although I’m not certain that the faculty exists to actually fulfill that mission at most schools, and perhaps it shouldn’t, given the mission of performing and publishing research, too. As much as I enjoy being an adjunct, a too-heavy reliance on such teachers is a bad thing for students. I know that my students don’t get my absolute best effort, owing to my day job, and I also am not a contributor to the academic life of the university beyond the class I teach.</p>
<p>Two things seem slightly more achievable to me, although every school is different: more flexibility in curriculum requirements, and more accessible scholarship. One starts to address the concerns of students like Katie and professors like Mindy. The other might start to repair the breach between the academy and the industry that serves neither well.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2013/04/28/academy-fight-song/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 28 Apr 2013 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Itemizer</title>
  <dc:creator>Derek Willis</dc:creator>
  <link>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2013/04/24/the-itemizer/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Here’s a little secret about me: I love campaign finance data.</p>
<p>Ok, so that’s <a href="https://twitter.com/campfinmoments">no secret at all</a>, and it’s probably unhealthy in some respects. But let’s face it, campaign finance data provides a rich source of information for stories, blog posts and tweets, in rough descending order of size and scope. There’s one thing that has always bugged me about how we reference campaign finance data online: the best that most of us can do when we link to a campaign filing is to link to a particular page, whether that’s <a href="http://query.nictusa.com/cgi-bin/dcdev/forms/C00271312/868832/sa/ALL">a list of contributors</a> or <a href="http://query.nictusa.com/cgi-bin/dcdev/forms/C00452144/868805/">a summary page</a>. Yet often we’re referencing a single transaction or line-item.</p>
<p>I started to think more about this after listening to <a href="http://ji2013.sched.org/event/2b8aa8249e92fce2f81c3a3ceccf68df?iframe=no&amp;w=680&amp;sidebar=no&amp;bg=no#.UXh_ClvWEbo">David Cohn talk about Circa at the Journalism Interactive conference</a> in February. <a href="http://cir.ca/about/">Circa</a> “is creating the first born-on-mobile news experience, delivering it in a format native to mobile devices, with an experience intuitive to mobile users,” and part of that means breaking down what we think of as stories into their essential components. Those usually are statements or facts of some kind that can readers into a larger story. This “atomization” of news, <a href="http://www.slideshare.net/JIConf/circa-message">as David called it in his presentation</a>, focuses tightly on the core elements of a story.</p>
<p>For people who work with data and love to cite it in stories, this is a good idea. It got me thinking about how we could do that for campaign finance data, where transactions are the smallest particle. What I’ve come up with, with the assistance of Aaron Bycoffe, is <a href="http://itemizer.herokuapp.com/">The Itemizer</a>, a simple app that takes itemized records from Federal Election Commission filings and allows you to link to them. If you want to specifically reference the $1,000 that the Society of American Florists PAC gave to Nydia Velazquez, <a href="http://itemizer.herokuapp.com/filing/868832/schedule/sa#VN89J1EW3Y1">now you can</a>.</p>
<p>When I say simple, <a href="https://github.com/dwillis/itemizer">I mean it</a>. It’s a Rails 3.2 app, but it could just as easily be implemented in Sinatra, given how small it is. The anchor links are based on the transaction IDs from the filings, so there’s no need to invent unique hashes or anything. Thanks to the <a href="http://nytimes.github.io/campaign_cash/">Campaign Cash</a> and <a href="http://nytimes.github.io/Fech/">Fech</a> Ruby gems, the page loads today’s filings and then constructs links to receipts and expenditures (other schedules are coming). Nothing is stored in a database - Campaign Cash pulls in the day’s filings from <a href="http://developer.nytimes.com/docs/campaign_finance_api/">The New York Times Campaign Finance API</a> and Fech processes individual filings on the fly. Although the default is to today’s filings, if you know the filing number, you can plug it and the schedule into the URL and it’ll just work.</p>
<p>Although it was relatively simple to build and deploy (thanks, Heroku!), I don’t expect the FEC to do something like this anytime soon, although I’d be happy if they did. More certainty, tighter focus, more direct references – these are good things for journalism. If you have ideas on improving The Itemizer, please join in. Or better yet, build one for a similar data set that you work with so even more people can benefit.</p>



 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://www.thescoop.org/archives/2013/04/24/the-itemizer/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2013 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
